<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great eater of Grayes-Inne, or The life of Mr. Marriot the cormorant. VVherein is set forth, all the exploits and actions by him performed; with many pleasant stories of his travells into Kent and other places. Also, a rare physicall dispensatory, being the manner how he makes his cordiall broaths, pills, purgations, julips, and vomits, to keep his body in temper, and free from surfeits. / By G.F. Gent.</title>
            <author>Fidge, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74874</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E667_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27357</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872162</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872162</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166185</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74874)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166185)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 102:E667[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great eater of Grayes-Inne, or The life of Mr. Marriot the cormorant. VVherein is set forth, all the exploits and actions by him performed; with many pleasant stories of his travells into Kent and other places. Also, a rare physicall dispensatory, being the manner how he makes his cordiall broaths, pills, purgations, julips, and vomits, to keep his body in temper, and free from surfeits. / By G.F. Gent.</title>
                  <author>Fidge, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 41, [1] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are sold by William Reybould at the Unicorne in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.F. = George Fidge.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriott, John, d. 1653.</term>
               <term>Food habits --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dispensatories --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166185:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Great Eater of <hi>Grayes-Inne,</hi> OR THE LIFE OF M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> MARRIOT THE CORMORANT.</p>
            <p>VVherein is ſet forth, all the Exploits and Actions by him performed; with many pleaſant Stories of his Travells into <hi>Kent</hi> and other places.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A RARE PHYSICALL DISPEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SATORY, BEING THE MANNER how he makes his Cordiall Broaths, <hi>Pills, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, Julips,</hi> and <hi>Vomits,</hi> to keep his Body in temper, and free from Surfeits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> G. F. <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are ſold by <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tam Reybould</hi> at the Unicorne in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:166185:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:166185:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER. His <hi>CHARACTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Ancients are of opinion that hee came of the race of the <hi>Centaures,</hi> and it may paſſe for currant, his upper part being leſſe then Man, and his lower more then Beaſt; no Horſe hath ſuch a ſwitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Stomack: He loves <hi>Cook</hi> and <hi>Kitchin,</hi> not ſo much for their Law as for their Names ſakes, and at <hi>Bacon</hi> his mouth waters; he knowes better how to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a Chyne of Beefe then a Cauſe, for he has more gutts then braines, and doubtleſſe there was a stout Thraſher ſpoyled when he was made a Lawyer: Hee is rather of the body Corporate then Politique; the round Table is no more to him then the ſquare, let him have meate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough (if ſuch a thing may be poſſible) he cares not if it be in a Wheelebarrow, and makes but one meale a day, that is from morning to night: He is a great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to a long Grace, and holds that 'tis time enough to give thanks when his Gorge is full, for then he hath
<pb facs="tcp:166185:3"/>moſt leaſure, he carryes a bottomleſſe <hi>Pit</hi> about him, by the Vulgar called his <hi>Maw,</hi> which has buryed more fleſh in a week, then <hi>Stepney Church-yard</hi> hath done <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes</hi> this dozen yeares; He has one virtue, that is, He drinks ſeldome, but when he falls to't he payes it, or ſome body for him; he ſayes he cannot endure to make a Sea of his Belly, but a Shambles he may for the ſlaughtered: He walks in the Street like <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> in Robes of Purple, but not like <hi>Dives</hi> in fine Linnen; for he holds Shirts unneceſſary, and his Cloaths are ſo Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namented with Patches, that many are buryed alive in them: He hath one property more then a Horſe, for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Stones weares out their ſhooes, his ſhooes weares out the Stones; he has the virtue of confidence, and is not nice of company: Provided there be eating, for he ſayes, of <hi>Idleneſſe comes no goodneſſe,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had rather exerciſe his Teeth then his Tongue: His company (tis confeſt) is more coſtly then a Whores, and for your avoiding it, Reader, I commend the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapters of his atchivements to your approbation, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring you, that nothing is ſet down in them, but what he hath truly acted, and ſo to the variety of them I leave thee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166185:3"/>
            <head>The firſt Generall notice taken of <hi>Marriots</hi> invincible Stomack.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Great Man of Little Law, was not generally taken notice of for a Tall Trencherman, till the beginning of the late Kings Reigne, who having gleaned ſome fragments of Law, was reſolved to make ſome body pay form them: and in a <hi>Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, (when Roſt beefe ſavours beſt) hee tooke up a Countrey Client (as a Whore does her Chance) and to <hi>We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mnſter</hi> he goes, where the firſt motion he made, was, to Break-faſt, ſaying, he ſhould be the better prepared for an Encounter at the Barre. The Gentleman in hopes to have ſucceſſe in his owne Motion, granted him his, and to Break-faſt they went, the Place deſigned for it was the Red Lyon in the Palace yard, where they took a Room, and the Gentleman bid the fellow bring a ſix penny-ſlice of Roſt-beefe, ſix penny worth (<hi>quoth</hi> Marriot) <hi>in wrath?</hi> what, doe you take me to be a Chicken
<note n="*" place="margin">Hee lookes more like an Oxe.</note> why, then bring twelve penny worth ſayes his Client, ſure that will ſerve, or elſe the Devil is in us: Not ſo neither (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) Come, let us be good Husbands, you ſhall ſee what a Caterer I will prove, and ſo enters the Kitchin: quoth he to the woman of the houſe, what ſhall I give thee for as much of thy Beefe as will ſuffice two,
<note place="margin">Marriot <hi>did not mean him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi>
                  </note> ten groats quoth the woman, ſye that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I know not how unreaſonable you may be with my Beefe (quoth ſhe) I have no meaſure of your Bellies,
<note n="*" place="margin">Nor he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his owne.</note> nor had I ever ſuch a queſtion put to me before: Well, well, ſaid <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> then we will goe another way to work, what is the price of the whole Surloyne? what the Devill will you doe with it quoth ſhee, carry it away I warrant thee quoth he, we will leave none behinde us, fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not: 'Tis ſix ſhillings quoth the woman, five ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> and bring it in, and ſo returnes to his Client, what have you done Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> quoth his Client, I have bid money for a pretty mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) if they will take it, and with that in comes the Beefe, at ſight whereof his Client ſtartles, why, what's the matter
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166185:4"/>man quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> afraid of good meate? or did you never ſee a Surloin of Beef before? Bleſſe me ſaid his Client what mean you, we have no more company to come to us. No matter ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> heres company enough, you know the proverb, <hi>The more the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier, but the fewer the better Cheer,</hi> and ſo <hi>Marriot</hi> ſell on, his Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent was ſo amazed, he had not power to eate a bit: What ſaid <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> does the ſight of my feeding take away your Stomack? ſee what tis to be ſo pulingly fedd. By this time the Wonder was over, and the Beefe wrought to the bones, the Gentleman ſmiling, asked if there were any more meate in the houſe, for he had eate nothing, Yes ſaid the fellow that waited, there is a cold Capon: Oh let us have it by all meanes quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> no meate ſo excellent as a cold Capon, why then ſaid his Client (and ſmiled) let's have it, <hi>You ſhall not ſtarve in a Cooks ſhop Mr.</hi> Marriot; your Cauſe ſhall fare the better for it quoth <hi>Marriot.</hi> Will you have any Sauce quoth the fellow, Sauce to a cold Capon (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) away you Raſcall, <hi>Hunger is the beſt ſauce when all is done.</hi> I proteſt Sir (quoth his Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent) you have an excellent faculty, I Sir (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) I would you had ſo good a ſtomack, ſo would not I (replyed his Client) for I ſhould ſtarve my Wife and Children then. The Capon was brought in, Sir (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) we muſt make all the haſt we can, the Court will ſit ſuddenly: I perceive Sir (quoth his Client you will looſe no time, oh 'tis a precious thing quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched the Capon, at which his Client laughed heartily, and ſaid 'tis the beſt frolique I ever paid for in <hi>London,</hi> I am glad it pleaſed you, Sir, quoth <hi>Marriot.</hi> The reckoning being paid, quoth the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the houſe, you are welcome Gentlemen, and for your part Sir (to <hi>Marriot</hi>) could you but drink as well as you can eate, you would be the beſt Gueſt comes to my houſe, provided you paid for what you called for, if I doe not, ſome body elſe ſhall I warrant thee woman: (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) I was not borne for my ſelfe only, and ſo trotted on to the Hall, where wee leave him to his ſocond Motion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166185:4"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>having his Motion granted, urged his Client to goe to dinner, and what happened.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArriot,</hi> though a Man of weake Judgement, yet of ſtrong Lungs, bellowed ſo loud at the Barre, that to be rid of him the Judges opened their eares (I cannot ſay their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding) and granted his Motion: Upon which <hi>Marriot</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed forth in open Court, Bleſſing on the Judges, and keep them in this mind ever. Now (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi> to his Client) what thinke you? have I not friends? yes, and good ones too you ſee, but what ſay you to a Dinner
<note n="*" place="margin">Marriot <hi>not in Commons.</hi>
                  </note>? 'tis that time a day (for he was too dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a perſon to be admitted into Commons among the reſt of his Function:) why (replied his Client) are you ready for a Dinner that made but now ſo ſtout a Breakfaſt? Ready
<note n="*" place="margin">Marriot <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
                  </note> and ready again (quoth <hi>Marriot.</hi>) Alas Sir, Meate quickly diſgeſts with men of my Calling, I have walked ſince, and talked ſince; and ſpent my Spirits in your Cauſe, a Noble refreſhment will be very ſeaſonable. Hark you Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> (quoth his Client) your Motions are very chargeable, are all your Clients at the coſt to finde you meate and money too? Yes, yes, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> ſome meate and ſome money does well, but you will have <hi>all and ſum</hi> where ever you come Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> quoth his Client. I take leſſe fees for my Motions (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) then any Man in Towne, but you take more meate then will ſerve three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore quoth his Client, and laughed heartily. Alas Sir, (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) my belly is not ſo deepe but it may be filled; marry and I will try that (quoth his client) if all the meate in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> will do it: And ſo his Client being reſolved to fathom his ungodly Paunch, carryed him to the houſe where they breakfaſted; but hee having made there ſo great a ſlaughter in the morning, that they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared to meet his Noons Encounter; but very civilly the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the houſe told him (being a good cuſtomer) that if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſay what he would have, it ſhould be dreſt in a trice: No quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> my Stomack is up, and I muſt have ſomething pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to appeaſe it, or my whole frame will be out of order, and ſo he marched into Kings ſtreet with a Stomack of no ſmall growth, in ſo ſhort a time, where, having ſearched every Cooks ſhop, that had a fit appearance to receive his Client (though a ſtye would ſerve him) and finding Proviſion fall ſhort of Expectation, all being ſpent before, <hi>Marriot</hi> began to <hi>rave,</hi> and ſwore the People had a <hi>minde to ſtarve him.</hi> At laſt, ſearching for his Prey
<note n="*" place="margin">That is, whom he may devour.</note>, eſpyed on his left hand
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166185:5"/>towards the three Tuns Tavern, a Dirty Tray full of dirtier
<note n="*" place="margin">Draffe is good enough for Swine.</note> meat of all ſorts, ſuch as had endured the ſury of the fire at leaſt a dozen times, and been drowned in Greace as often: The houſe, or rather a Den,
<note n="*" place="margin">The houſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</note> out of which came a ſmoak able to choake a horſe, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly from the time of its building never had been befriended with Sun. The Cook himſelf of griſly hue, appeared as though he had bin bred up in <hi>Pluto's</hi> Kitchin: His <hi>Maudlin,</hi> or <hi>Shee-thing,</hi> of like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, with an Apron of perfect Sluttery, and of countenance able (a Man would think) to overcome the moſt reſolure and ſtrongeſt appetite. Yet <hi>Marriot</hi> no whit daunted, encouraged his Client to ſtep over, ſaying, <hi>See Sir, where the hand of Providence ha's dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted us, I proteſt I began to faint.</hi> His Client perceiving his gaſtly countenance, fearing he would eate him if he were kept longer from meate, reſolved to endure the Plague of the houſe, rather then ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by his tyrannous Jawes, and ſo with Noſe not <hi>Scent-free,</hi> he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the inchanted Caſtle, with Giantick <hi>Marriot; Marriot</hi> poyſes the Tray, and finds it anſwerable to his Stomack, quoth he, friend, what wilt thou take for as much meate as I can eate, this Gentleman is not at this time for eating: Why, Sir, (quoth the fellow) one of theſe pieces will ſerve two men, and you ſhall dine on one of them for twelve pence: No quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I am a Gentleman, and will not be confin'd to one Diſh, I muſt take here a bit and there a bit; troth I feare (quoth the fellow) it will ſpoile the fale of them, but if if you pleaſe to give me three ſhillings, you ſhall make your meale on them; thou art an honeſt fellow (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) and ſhalt have it: So up they went to a Roome where no light had ever been ſeen, ſave Candle-light, and ſtunck worſe then the Shambles Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or the Bear-garden. His Client not able to endure their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty accommodation, would have departed, and at the Bell Tavern have ſtayed for him: but <hi>Marriot</hi> would not permit it, ſaying, <hi>Sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men miſeris ſocios habuiſſe doloris.</hi> Up came the meate, not ordered in ſeverall Diſhes, but clapt together in the Tray, as it ſtood upon the Stall; but whether it was to blunt the edg of his Stomack, or for want of diſhes, is diſputable; but <hi>Marriot</hi> to ſhew he feared no colours
<note n="*" place="margin">For the meat had all.</note> fell on Pell, mell, and ſo defeated, or vanquiſhed three of the pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the whole body being but ſixe, but of ſuch mixtures, as an Army made up of <hi>Switzers, French, Dutch, Spanyards,</hi> &amp;c. So this hodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podge of <hi>Veale, Mutton, Porke, Beefe,</hi> and ſo forth. The
<note n="*" place="margin">In plain Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a Dirty cloath or Rag.</note> 
                  <hi>Maudlin</hi> of the houſe perceiving how magnanimouſly he went on, and fearing the ſpoil of the reſt, ran down to her Maſter, &amp; told him that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill was come in the likeneſs of a Lawyer, and had eaten three of the biggeſt pieces, and was endangering the other. The fellow
<note n="*" place="margin">Fearing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God nor Devill.</note> ranne up ſtairs, but before hee came, <hi>Marriot</hi> had made an end of two of them, and was ready to fall upon the other: You Dogg quoth the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166185:5"/>fellow, and ſeized on the Tray and the remaining piece of meate; You Raſcall quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> give me the meate: Sirrah (quoth the fellow) beeſt thou the Devill or his Dam, I will have money for the meate thou haſt eaten, <hi>Maudlin</hi> fetch me a Conſtable, at which his Client was ready to burſt with laughter, you Knave (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) I will not give thee a penny till I have had my bargain, you ſhall know ſirrah who I am, and that I will ſtraight quoth the fellow, and at him he flies, Sir (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) bear witneſſe, I am a Lawyer, the Devil's in the Lawyer then (quoth the fellow) and I will beate him out of thee: Down falls <hi>Marriot,</hi> his Client not able to endure longer, makes his way towards the ſtairs, thinking to make up the ſportby his leaving them; but the ſtairs being dark, downe tumbles his Clyent, in comes <hi>Maudlin</hi> with the Conſtable, the Conſtable ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes on the Gentleman, immediately <hi>Marriot</hi> was heard to cry out, the Conſtable ſecured the Gentleman, and then went up, where he found <hi>Marriot's</hi> hat off, his Gowne over his Ears
<note n="*" place="margin">Note the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of them.</note>, and his Blew bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches diſcovered, Bleſſe me quoth the Conſtable, what have we here? A diſtreſſed Gentleman (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) thou lyeſt (quoth the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low) thou art no Gentleman,
<note n="*" place="margin">His Gentility queſtioned.</note> for if thou wert thou wouldſt pay me for my meat; ſirrah ſirrah quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> thou art a Knave, I will make thee ſtand to thy bargain, thou ſhalt be hang'd firſt, and at him he flies againe: come, cries the Conſtable, a Juſtice of Peace ſhall end this difference, with all my heart quoth the fellow, and mine too (quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi>) I can ſhew my face where thou dareſt not thine. So downe the Conſtable had them, to goe before the Juſtice, but his Client being unwilling to appeare further in the buſineſſe, offered to pay the fellow for his meate: As I am a Chriſtian (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) but you ſhall not, I will have out my bargain, or I will not pay him a penny for his meate. What was the bargain, quoth the Conſtable, I was to make a meale on his meate (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) for three ſhillings, and he has eaten me five pieces (quoth the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low) as bigge
<note n="†" place="margin">He ſhews the piece.</note> as this, and would have this too. The Conſtable laughed heartily, and told <hi>Marriot</hi> it was a ſhamefull thing, and moſt unreaſonable. I am a Lawyer (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) and know 'tis no ſhamefull thing for a Man to eate his
<note n="†" place="margin">Were there more ont.</note> meate. Sirrah (quoth the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low) it was none of thine, I will be paid for it, and ſo to a Juſtice they went: The Conſtable there opened the matter to the Juſtice, <hi>Marriot</hi> pleaded his bargain, the Fellow made his defence, and ſaid, he thought he had bargained with a <hi>Man,</hi> but he proved a <hi>Monſter,</hi> It is all one for that (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) a bargain is a bargain, and I will have right if there be any Juſtice
<note n="†" place="margin">As though he doubted it.</note> in the Kingdom. The Juſtice (being of <hi>Gotam</hi> breed) checkt the fellow, &amp; told him that a bargain was a bargain,
<note n="†" place="margin">Every foole can ſpeak as he is taught.</note> and he would recover it againſt him, and therefore ordered the fellow (for preventing his future trouble) to reſtore <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:166185:6"/>the other piece of meate, and to take his three ſhillings for full ſatisfaction. Well (quoth the fellow) if it muſt be ſo, hee ſhall eate it in my ſight, and the Devill doe him good with it: Good reaſon too, quoth the Juſtice, but not in my houſe (quoth the fellow) I'le ſee him hangd firſt: I care not where I eate it (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) and yet I'le eate it where I pleaſe: Not ſo neither quoth the Juſtice, you muſt eate it where the bargain was made. Oh good your Worſhip (quoth the fellow) puniſh me not ſo, unleſſe you Order him to call for drink proportionable: Well Sir, (quoth the Juſtice) give him twelve pence more, and eate it where you pleaſe Sir, I'le eate it in the ſtreet firſt quoth <hi>Marriot;</hi> away, away, quoth his Client, it ſhall be ſo, we but treſpaſſe upon this Gentlemans patience, friend deliver him his bargaine, and thou ſhalt have foure ſhillings, that's twelve pence more then my bargain (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) it goes neer my heart to give it him. They departed from the Juſtices, and returned to the Cooks Cell-doore, for into it he was not to be admitted, the meate was brought forth, the money paid, and <hi>Marriot</hi> put the meat in his ſleeve
<note n="*" place="margin">'Twas not the firſt time he had done ſo.</note>: Sirrah ſirrah, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I ſhall know you for a Knave hereafter, and ſhun thy houſe as I would a Priſon. Bridewell is fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for you then a civill houſe, quoth the fellow, and ſet the boyes at him, that <hi>Marriot</hi> became in danger, which his <hi>Client</hi> perceiving, ſlunk through <hi>Stevens</hi> Alley, and left him to the mercy of the boyes. <hi>Marriot</hi> obſerving the multitude to increaſe, and fearing leſt hee ſhould looſe his meate in the combuſtion, ſtalked
<note n="*" place="margin">His uſuall pace.</note> along the ſtreet, ſometimes ſnapping at the meate, and ſometimes at the boyes: Be quiet children, quoth he, I am a man
<note n="*" place="margin">In his owne conceit.</note>, and ſhall— then he ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes downe a peice as big as his fiſt, and that is of no ſmall ſize, till by degrees he had made an end of it all, without the help of bread or drink, and ſo laughing at the boyes and his fancy of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his meate from them, kept on his Pace with the boyes at his heeles, till hee came to his Lodging, and there received his firſt ſhout and acclamation to be no Innes of Court Dumplin, but a man of a large Colon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:166185:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Marriots <hi>ſecond Encounter, with his voyding a Worme.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Marriot</hi> being invited to Dinner to a private houſe by ſome Gentlemen, was met in the ſtreet by ſome other Gentlemen, who obſerving how he ſweat with going an unuſuall pace, apprehended that he was upon ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of meeting, <hi>alias</hi> eating, and his haſt betrayed his feares of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming too late, and ſo they having a diſpoſition for mirth, reſolved to ſtay his Journey. Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> (quoth one of them) why ſo faſt? I pray Sir forbeare (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) my buſineſs is of concernment, the ſtate of your body I warrant quoth the other Gentleman: Sir (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) pray let me goe
<note n="*" place="margin">Marriot <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry.</hi>
                  </note>, what haſt, what haſt, quoth the Gentleman: Well Gentlemen quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> you may do me more harm in an houre, then you will do me good in ten, how know you that (quoth the other) You are a Man of good Intelligence, Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> what News, what Newes? I have no more to do with News then Newes hath to do with me (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) pray let me
<note n="*" place="margin">Oh to ſee his face now.</note> goe. Suppoſe (quoth one of them) I ſhould bring you Newes of a Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, were there any harme in it? <hi>Marriot</hi> lickt his lips, and ſaid, pray Gentlemen do me not thus much preiudice, there are ſome that ſtay for me: What to do (ſayes the Gentlemen) this is Vacation time, you have not Law Suits to follow, and held him faſt by the Wriſt, <hi>Marriot</hi> began to
<note n="*" place="margin">You cannot blame him.</note> ſtrive, at which the people that flocked about him laughed heartily. Gentlemen (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) I pray let me goe, or I'le call a Conſtable: To call a Conſtable you mean (quoth the Gentlemen) and therefore 'tis beſt keeping you here, with that the People laughed out-right, why good people, good people, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> will you let a Gentleman be thus obſtructed in his Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? What are your Occaſions Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> (quoth one of them) are they urgent? I, in truth are they quoth <hi>Marriot;</hi> what, in matter of Dinner quoth the Gentlemen? You have the right of it Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) as I am a Chriſtian: Why ſeriouſly (quoth one of them) nothing but your Stomack
<note n="†" place="margin">If that will not, I know not what will.</note> ſhould part us. I proteſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) I lye not. The Gentlemen having had mirth ſufficient with him, lets looſe his Wriſt; which no ſooner done, but <hi>Marriot</hi> takes his run as faſt as his heavy heels could carry him, At which all the People gave a ſhout, and the boyes after him. At laſt <hi>Marriot</hi> reached the place appointed, where he was no ſooner entered, but he comes firſt in the Kitchin, and finding his Deten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had wronged him much, the laſt Courſe being ready to goe in,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166185:7"/>fell upon a bowle of cold Creame that ſtood on the Dreſſer, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched it in the twinkling of a Gloworm. The laſt Courſe going in, he enters with it, and there to the Gentlemen he relates the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his ſtay. Alack (quoth the Gentlemen) you have done your ſelfe a great deale of wrong, Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> and us too. Nay quoth Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> I have not done it, but the Knaves that held me in the Street, but I hope I ſhall recover the time I have loſt to all your Contents, and ſo fell on a dozen of Pigeons, and a leaze of ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rabbets; which having devoured (to the wonder of the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) quoth he, Gentlemen, I doe not like this pidling diſhes, have you no ſubſtantiall Beefe or Mutton left in the houſe, and ſo what was remaining, was brought in, which he as eaſily deſtroyed as the other, and was ready for more: But <hi>Marriot</hi> being over-heated with coming, and falling firſt on the cold Cream, and drinking ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after it, found ſuch quarrelling in his Guts, that he was unable to ſit longer at Table, and before he could get from thence, ſhewed ſome teſtimony of his looſe Condition, to the prejudice of all their Noſes there preſent. His Vocative caſe made the Gentlemen weary of his Company; and finding him worſe and worſe, they cauſed a Porter to be called for, and bargained with him to lead him to his Lodging; but before the Porter got halfe way, he was ſo ſtrong of Monſieur Sir Reverence, that he was not to be endured. The Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſpying a fellow with a Wheelbarrow, called him, and told him the Gentleman was ſick, and if he would carry him home, he would be very well paid for his paines, for hee was a Perſon of Quality. The fellow with hopes of profit, was armed againſt Senior <hi>le Faugh,</hi> and takes him in, and carries his Worſhip, but ſee his fate! he was unhappily carried that way where the Gentlemen had made ſport with him in the Morning, ſo that the Shop-keepers and Boys, eſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in that caſe, ran out and cryed, The great Eater has over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaten himſelf; to whom <hi>Marriot</hi> ſtil cryed, good Chriſtians forbear, and do not mocke a dying man, ha quoth the Boyes, This is the great Eater of <hi>Grays Inne:</hi> A pox upon you quoth the Wheelbarrow fellow, art thou the Cormorant? I would have ſeen you hang'd (had I knowne ſo much) before you ſhould have come into my Barrow; Out, out, in the Devils Name, it is no charity to preſerve thy life: And ſo out poor <hi>Marriot</hi> was thrown in a pittifull pickle; oh quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> is there no Chriſtian-minded People among you? At laſt two women Tankerd-bearers, took pitty of him, had him into a houſe, and waſhed him, and at Night was led to his Lodging, where he was no ſooner ſate downe, but he was taken as though he had quick ſilver in his guts, and nothing would ſatisfie him but a Doctor, who almoſt as ſoon as ſent for, came. Alas (quoth the Doctor) Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> you have taken a ſurfeit with eating too much; fye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye (quoth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166185:7"/>
                  <hi>Marriot</hi>) Sir, you are miſtaken, I could have eaten thrice as much: You muſt take a Purge quoth the Doctor, I purge too much alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I quoth the Doctor, but this proceeds from the malignity of the Cauſe, the effect of which being taken away, this purging ceaſeth. Say you ſo Sir (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) pray uſe me well, and let me have it as ſoone as poſſible, you ſhall have it made ready to night (quoth the Doctor) fit to take to morrow, I ſhall dye before quoth <hi>Marriot;</hi> why then quoth the Doctor, you ſhall have it to take to night, and ſo went his wayes to make ready the Purge, which being finiſhed, <hi>Marriot</hi> received, and a while before he went to bed, tooke it; about two hours after his being abed, it began to work, and at laſt he felt a long thing come from him, at ſight whereof hee cryed out, oh the Devil, the Devil, whereupon all the houſe was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed. The Doctor was ſent for, who, when he ſaw the Worme, told him that it was a Worme that had long time bred in his body, and would have come to a more perfect growth, had not that acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of eating the cold Creame (which is an Enemie to thoſe kinde of Wormes) and drinking ſuddenly after it, curdled it, and ſo ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and killed the Worme; for which reſolvement, Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> gave him not only thanks, but payed him for his Purge, and to this day keeps the Worme (dryed up) in his Chamber, which was then about three yards long. But it is conceived by the Wiſe, that it left behind at that time, young ones, which are grown to a greater big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as may appeare by the growth of his Stomack, but whether it be or not, Time and ſuch another Surfeit will produce, and untill which time you muſt have patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>How the Lord</hi> Grandiſon <hi>ſerved Mr.</hi> Marriot <hi>at Madam</hi> Pikes, <hi>and how afterward cauſed him to fright the Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and what happened.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY this time <hi>Marriot</hi> was grown Famous in his Art, inſomuch, that happy was that Noble perſon that could get him to make ſport. It hapned that the Lord <hi>Grandiſons</hi> Coach paſſing by the New Exchange, when his Footman eſpyed Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> walking alone, he ſoone acquainted his Lord therewith, who being merrily diſpoſed, ſent for him, and deſired him to come into the Coach to him, and now he has him to Madam <hi>Pikes,</hi> where was good Wine, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166185:8"/>ſuch knacks as Lords uſe to have: But Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> began to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, ſaying, I hope you have not brought me hither to look only on taftaty Tarts, or a diſh of Coxcombs: My Lord, this is not meate for me, I love Beefe, Mutton, Veale, or Pork, that is meate which will endure ſome cutting: I pray my Lord ſet by your Ferboon Kickſhaws: Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> ſaid my Lord, you ſhall firſt drinke your belly full; <hi>Marriot</hi> being unwilling, yet at the laſt, in hopes of meate, took up his cups handſomely, but his brain being weake, was ſoon drunke. My Lord <hi>Grandiſon</hi> ſends for a Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ber to ſhave all the haire off his beard; which being done, they got a large looſe Gowne, and pulled off his owne Cloaths, and put the Gowne on him, with Head-cloaths and Apron, dreſſing him like a Bawd. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi> being ſo drunk that he knew not what they did, was in this ſhape led to the Coach, and thence he was carried to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> where being conveyed to a Chamber, through which the Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> was to paſſe, they let him in a Chaire, and left him; The Arch-Biſhop coming through the roome, ſtarts at the ſight of him, ſaying to his Gentleman-Uſher, I do much wonder how this drunken Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould come here; <hi>Marriot</hi> being not full afleep, ſaid, <hi>I</hi> am no Woman, <hi>I</hi> am a Man, and a Lawyer; the Biſhop much wondring at him, aſſured himſelfe that ſome body had put him in that place to affront him, and now begins to queſtion <hi>Marriot,</hi> who for his part was not able to ſpeak for himſelfe: but my Lord <hi>Grandiſon</hi> ſtept into the roome, and ended the controverſie, by ſending <hi>Marriot</hi> away, telling the Biſhop that he came ſo diſguiſed only to aske pardon for his faults: The Biſhop was angry at his ſaying, but could not helpe himſelfe. My Lord <hi>Grandiſon</hi> gave <hi>Marriot</hi> a ſuite of Cloaths for his pains, which to this day, though greaſie, are to be ſeen on his backe, and is very loath to leave them, for the very fancy of the paſtimes he had in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>eate a Gammon of Bacon, and would not pay for it, and had like to have been ſtoned.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> deſirous to ſee <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Fair, went up Hoſier Lane, and there eſpyed a Gammon of Bacon ſet forth on the Stall (as the Cuſtom is at Fares) which put him in mind of Eating. So <hi>Marriot</hi> walks gravely and ſoberly in, and asketh the woman of the houſe to ſhew a Room; which being done, quoth <hi>Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot</hi> to the woman, I ſaw Bacon in your Shop, and marry that is there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166185:8"/>quoth the Woman, and the very beſt in all the Fare Ile aſſure you. A man may have a cut at it (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) I hope, and pay for it, may he not? I bleſſing on your heart quoth the Woman, and ſpare not. Gramercy quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> thou ſeemeſt to be a good body; do you want any Company Sir, quoth the Woman, here is
<note n="*" place="margin">They were Whores.</note> Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the houſe Berlady (which is indeed the onely furniture of all Fares) No quoth <hi>Marriot</hi> J thanke thee Woman, not at this time, prithee fetch thy Bacon. The woman brought her Bacon, quoth ſhe bleſſing on your good heart Sir, fall on and ſpare not, which ſpeech (as J take it) ſhee might have ſpared, for he was reſolved to that without her Counſell. The Woman was ſcarce returned into the Shop, but <hi>Marriot</hi> had drunk up his ſingle pot of Beere, eate two Rolls, and pickt the very bones of the Bacon, which had had but a ſmall ſlice cut off it before: <hi>Marriot</hi> comes into the Shop, quoth he J have quickely done, ſo it ſeems Sir quoth ſhee; there is twelve pence for thy Bacon quoth he, J will come another time and be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with thee: God bleſſe you Sir quoth ſhe, and ſend you well to do, the woman not thinking he had eaten all, and being buſied in her Shop, could not preſently goe to ſee what ſpoile had been made, thought her ſelf well paid, and <hi>Marriot</hi> went his ways into the Fare; but it ſo happened that <hi>Marriot</hi> came that way back, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man having found out the Deceit, was curſing him deeply, and call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him all the names that could be. At laſt ſhe eſpyed <hi>Marriot,</hi> oh there is the Rogue quoth ſhee that eate up my whole Gammon of Bacon, and hath undone me, J will be the death of him, thou Rogue quoth ſhee, pay me for my Bacon: Why Woman, Woman, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> have patience, did not J pay thee twelve pence: A pox up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you for a Gormandizing Knave, is twelve peace enough for a large Gammon of Bacon? Goe goe, you are a huſwife, quoth <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> and would have had me been naught in thy houſe; Thou lyeſt like a whorſon Knave quoth the Woman, and at him ſhe flew: But <hi>Marriot</hi> was made too ſtrong with her Bacon for her to overcome, and ſo downe ſhee came, you Jade quoth he, J'le make you know your ſelfe. Murder, murder, quoth the Woman, out you great Rogue quoth the boyes, will you beate a woman? and ſo they threw ſtones at him. <hi>Marriot</hi> ſeeing company flock about him, and every one had a fling at him, took his runne, and the boyes hooting after him, till he came neere his Lodging, where he was reſcued by the Porters in <hi>Grayes-Inne</hi> Lane.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:166185:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>How Mr.</hi> Marriot <hi>was invited to Dinner, and how he conveyed meate away, but met with</hi> Stump <hi>the Wine-pot Carrier of the Fleece in</hi> Holborn, <hi>and of the terrible Battle fought between them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAſter <hi>Marriot</hi> was invited to the Globe Tavern in Chancery Lane by ſome Gentlemen to Dinner, upon a Wager, that hee ſhould not deſtroy the Dinner that was provided for themſelves. Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> came according to their invitation, and was welcomed, and bid fall too, which <hi>Marriot</hi> was as ready to do, as they to deſire, and on he fell, drawing his dreadfull Knife, and laying about him as he had been madde, to the ſpeedy deſtruction of the Dinner; whereat the Compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laughed, and ſaid, why Gramercy Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> you ſhew your ſelfe free from Deceit; but <hi>Marriot</hi> it ſeems had been at it ſome where elſe a little before, that had ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up ſome of his Chinks, and ſo could not devour all but becauſe they ſhould take no Exceptions, hee clearely conveyed the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into his falſe bagg which he had about him for the purpoſe, that none could diſcover his ſlight of hand but ſuch another <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> as himſelf. The Gentlemen became heartily merry at his <hi>Leger de Fons,</hi> &amp; drank to him: but <hi>Marriot:</hi> being weary of drinking as wel as eating, made his excuſe to go down to exerciſe his Poſteriors, which they granted him, and deſired his return: but he no ſooner was got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten down, but homeward he goes with more then his ordinary pace, and in <hi>Grayes Inne</hi> met with <hi>Stump</hi> (ſo called becauſe of his Wooden leg) quoth <hi>Stump,</hi> how now you <hi>Monſtrum</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Lame Latine.</note> 
                  <hi>Morendum,</hi> where have you been, and pulled him by the ſleeve, and clapping him about the Breeches and Pockets, felt ſomething more then ordinary, at which <hi>Marriot</hi> called him Raſcall, and pulled his Bag forth: Oh ſirrah, quoth <hi>Stump,</hi> what Beggar-woman have you robbed, ha? or haſt thou taken it out of the Priſoners Basket: You Raſcall, quoth <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> I will breake thy bones; goe, goe, quoth <hi>Stump,</hi> thou art a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous hound, and fitter to be hang'd, then to live; with that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi> ſtrikes <hi>Stump,</hi> and <hi>Stump</hi> ſtrikes <hi>Marriot,</hi> till both lay on the ground. <hi>Marriot's</hi> Ruffe was torne by <hi>Stump,</hi> and <hi>Stump's</hi> wooden leg was broke; the ſcraps or fragments of the Feaſt were throwne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and <hi>Stump</hi> lay on the ground, not able to riſe for want of his leg. <hi>Marriot</hi> thought he had been revenged enough on <hi>Stump,</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers up his pieces of meate, and goes his way: You Rogue, you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166185:9"/>Rogue, quoth <hi>Stump,</hi> could I but follow you, J would mall your Ugly hide for you; but <hi>Marriot</hi> kept on his Pace, and minded him not, and <hi>Stump</hi> at laſt by the helpe of a Porter, was carryed to the Joyners, and there had his leg ſet right again, and ſo went about his buſineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>was ſent for downe to a Knights houſe, and how he was ſerved there.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Knight living in <hi>Kent,</hi> having many Gallants at his houſe in the Chriſtmas time, could not have ſport enough he thought to give them Entertainment: And ſtill ſtudying and invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for freſh mirth to make them laugh, at laſt it came in his head to ſend to <hi>London</hi> for Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> on purpoſe that his friends might be the more heartily Merry, which as ſoone as thought upon, the Knight put in practice, and calling his Man to him, gave him 20. s. and commanded him to ſaddle a couple of Horſes, and make all the haſt be could to <hi>London,</hi> and deliver this Letter to Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> you will heare of him in <hi>Grayes-Inne</hi> Lane, and deſire him not to faile to come along with you to me. The Letter was as followeth,</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I <hi>Have been beholding to you often when I was in</hi> London, <hi>for your good Company, and now I have laid fifty pounds that you will come with my Serva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>, and therefore I pray faile me not, for you ſhall not onely have all the Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment my houſe will afford you for a fortnight, or longer, as you pleaſe, if your Occaſions will permit you, but alſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie you for your loſs of time, and ever remain,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your friend to ſerve you, J. S.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>THe Knight having diſpatched his Servant, went in to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and told them that he had ſent for one that would make them all heartily merry, and be hoped shortly to have him there;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166185:10"/>the Gentleman's friends enquired what he was, quoth the Knight, did you ever heare of one <hi>Marriot</hi> of Grayes-Inne? who <hi>Marriot</hi> the Great Eater quoth one of them? the very ſame replyed the Knight, troth and he will make good ſport indeed quoth one of them; what is he quoth another? he does pretend to the Law quoth the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but is he ſo great an Eater ſaid another? you ſhall ſee that when he comes quoth the Knight. The fellow followed his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons given him, and juſt as he was enquiring for Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> a Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in <hi>Grayes-Inne Lane</hi> ſhewed the Servant t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Man, who was cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Boyes, he coming from <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Lane</hi> with the foure heinges of a Sheep on his Arme, and three Bullocks Livers in a ſtring on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arme, jeering him with the Loyne of Mutton he had borrowed, hook, and all in <hi>Weſtm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſter.</hi> The ſervant began to ſuſpect that his Maſter had a plot to have him beaten, perceiving ſuch a tumult following the Man he was ſent too, hee being but a raw Countrey fellow; but <hi>Marriot</hi> at laſt got into the houſe, and the boyes after a great ſhout departed. They were no ſooner gone, but the Country fellow tooke upon him the Courage (which he durſt not before
<note n="*" place="margin">Seeing his ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Looks.</note>) to come up towards <hi>Marriots</hi> Lodging, and there very valiently knocked, and deſired to ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> the ſervant of the houſe told him he was newly gone up, but he would call him if the fellow pleaſed to come in, which he did, and was directed to go up to him in a little Chamber; The fellow knocked ſoftly, but unawares to <hi>Marriot,</hi> who haſtily coming forth with an Apron before him like a Butcher: Friend, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> would you ſpeak with me, yes Sir, ſaid he, I have a Letter for you, and ſo gave him the Letter; Which <hi>Marriot</hi> having read, and being tickled with the Conceit of ſo good Entertainment, pulled off his Apron, and made his Apology for having it on, ſaying, Friend, I am but a lone Man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my meate my ſelfe, which makes me appeare thus uncouth, but I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>im my ſelfe up preſently,
<note n="*" place="margin">On goes his purple Robes.</note> and along with you I will go, his meate he put into a Barrell wherein was ſowre ſmall Ale, to the end it might be well ſouſed againſt his returne, and ſo began to fit himſelfe for the Journey, He firſt pulled out a paire of ſhooes <hi>(for thickneſſe may be three paire)</hi> out of a hole, as for Bootes he had none; Then he tooke great care for a Sword, and at laſt got an old ruſty Hanger of the Cutler over againſt his Lodging,
<note place="margin">He would not ſtay to have a Frienge ſet on.</note> and for a Belt, cut an old Leather paire of Breeches, which had been ſome Paviers, into ſeverall pieces, and tyed the ends together, and ſo the Gallant was ready for his Journey, and went along with the Countrey fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to the place where the Horſes ſtayed; and being come, quoth the fellow, Sir, I thinke it very wholſome to take a Repaſe or ſo of meate before we ſet forward; with all my heart quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of your good motion, and ſo <hi>Marriot</hi> went to beſpeak Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166185:10"/>which was halfe a dozen pound of Sauſages, and a ſtewed Loin of Mutton, which was immediately got ready, and brought in, quoth the fellow, ſure Sir here's too much; be not deceived Friend, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I warrant thee thou wilt find no ſuch thing, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too little, and ſo they fell too,
<note place="margin">As it appeared by the fellowes ſhare.</note> but before the fellow got one Sauſage downe, <hi>Marriot</hi> had eaten a pound, which made the fellow ſtare. How now, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> what think you now? think quoth the fellow, I think I ſhall get nought for my money. The Sauſages being diſpatched, he fell on the ſtewed Mutton, nay quoth the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, Sir, pray give me leave to come into play with you; but <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi> ſo ordered the buſineſs, that the fellow had but a ſmall Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt. <hi>Marriot</hi> laughed heartily to ſee the fellow looke ſo at him, and ſaid, alas honeſt Friend, thy Maſter ſends for me to make him ſport, and I ſhall do it I warrant him: This <hi>Breakfaſt</hi> is but a pidling Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to ſtay my Stomack, I could have put him to greater charge if I had been ſo minded, but I reſerve that till I come to his houſe. Well Sir, quoth the fellow, I commend you, you have a good ſtroke with your Teeth. Hark you Friend, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I know it is your Maſters will that I ſhall be at no charges, and therefore pay the <hi>Reckoning,</hi> &amp; let us be going; Well if it muſt be ſo, it muſt be ſo,
<note place="margin">He wanted a Ladder.</note> quoth the fellow, &amp; ſo called for the horſes to be brought forth. The horſes being brought forth, <hi>Marriot</hi> endeavoured to get up on his, but the weight of his poſteriors, and the goutineſſe of his ſhooes hindered him, ſo that the fellow laughed, and took down the ſtirrup Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to let in his ugly hoofs, and then ſhouldered the Great Booby into the Saddle: Oh quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I hope the Horſe trots not! I am but a bad Rider, and therefore pray ride faire and ſoftly, and ſo on they went to their Journeyes end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>was entertained by the Knight, and the ſport they had with him.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Knight hearing that Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> was come, went out to meet him, where <hi>Marriot</hi> was unbinding his ſhooes and ſtockings, and vviping them with a wiſpe of ſtraw, the Knight bid him welcome, and asked him how he did, I tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k you Sir quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I am very well, but your ſplattering Nagge hath done my Shooes and Stockings a ſhillings worth of harme, I will make you reparations for any harme my horſe hath done you, and therefore pray walke in, Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> walke in, and dry your ſelfe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166185:11"/>there is a good ſire in the Kitchin: So going to the Fire with him, bid him ſit down, a Chair was brought him, and he ſate down, and then the Knight bid the Butler fetch a bottle of Sack, and drank to Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> I thank you Sir, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> fill him a Beer-glaſſe quoth the Knight, I thank you Sir quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I had rather eate then drink; Supper will be ready ſtreight quoth the Knight, <hi>Tom,</hi> Cook, make haſt with it, all the haſt that poſſible can be (Sir) ſaid the <hi>Cooke.</hi> Come Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> (quoth the Knight) I have ſome Friends within would gladly enjoy your Company, ſhall we into the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour? I am at your Commandment Sir, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> and with a Spanyards ſtately gate, he paced into the Parlour after the Knight, but his hobbled ſhoes made ſuch a Noyſe, that the Knight looked ſtil behind him, thinking his Malt horſe had followed him. The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, made their Civill Salute to Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> the Ladies fell a gigling at his Clouted ſhooes, what (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) Ladies are you laughing already? what will you do anon? <hi>by Lakins</hi> you ſhall have laughing enough Gallants, why that is well ſaid Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> quoth the Knight, pray take notice of my Friends, theſe are Gentlemen and Ladies of the Countrey, and ſuch as may merrit your friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> I am theirs, I am theirs, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> but your Raſcally <hi>Cooke methinks</hi> ſtayes ſomething long, fye on theſe delaies, I would he had as good a <hi>Stomack</hi> as I,
<note n="†" place="margin">The Knight would not have kept him then for five hundred pounds a yeare.</note> and then J am ſure he would make more haſt of Supper. Fear not Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> quoth the Knight, it will come immediately, and ſo gave Order to make all the haſt he could. Sir, quoth one of the Gentlemen, what Newes at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don?</hi> J ſeldome talke before Meales quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> after Supper J am for you: With that one of the Ladies ſtept towards him, J pray Sir (quoth ſhee) were you ever married? What to do Lady (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) what to do, is Supper coming yet? J perceive (quoth the Lady) you have more mind on your Supper then on a Wife. Why truly (quoth <hi>Marriot</hi>) a Wife is but an unneceſſary Diſh, and may ſerve to come well as the laſt Courſe, and ſo to be ſerved laſt (quoth the Lady) well, then be pleaſed to receive your <hi>Idoll</hi> (which was the meate newly brought in) and that I ſhall, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> you ſhall ſee willingly. Downe they ſate; quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> Gentlemen, let no Man have more manners then will do him good; for my part, I ſee the meate before me, and if any man has a better <hi>Stomack</hi> let him ſhew it, I am not aſhamed of mine, and ſo Gallants, by your leave, which was the word to be given, and thereupon <hi>Marriot</hi> fell upon the Spoile, and made <hi>havocke</hi> of what e're came before him, that the <hi>Cooke</hi> had much ado to make Diſhes ready for the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo faſt as he was ready for them; but there was no ſcarcity, the which <hi>Marriot</hi> tooke Notice of, ſaid, Sir I perceive you keep a good houſe, the like plenty be in it for ever. Amen (quoth one of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:166185:11"/>Ladies ſoftly) but keep thee from it good Lord I beſeech thee. I know the reaſon now Sir (quoth another Lady) why you will not marry; good Lady quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> ſpare your talking, I ſhall finde time enough to play when my <hi>worke</hi> is done. It being Chriſtmas time, as well Great as little Pyes were ſet before him: Quoth <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> as for your Diminitive Pies, I ſhal ſpare them, becauſe they are not worth my Anger; but as for the Towring Wals of the Gooſe and Turkie one, let them expect Demoliſhing, and ſo placed his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines of Bartery againſt them, and not admitting any Parley, made his Breaches ſuddenly, and ſo deſperately, one would have thought him a ſtout Engineer. Now the Ladies begin to look one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with pittiful Countenances, one of them ſetting all the mear and Pies that were unrouted in Battaile row, to hold him in Play while they roſe
<note n="†" place="margin">They feared he would eate them.</note> from the Table. The Gentlemen that were preſent laughed heartily to ſee the Ladies in this feare, and whiſpered them not to be ſo ſimple to think he vvould doe them any harme; vvhy quoth one of the Ladies, the Devill certainely is in him, and one ſo poſſeſt cares not vvhat hee does; troth He truſt him not quoth ſhee, nor I neither, quoth another, and roſe from the Table, and the reſt of the Ladies with them, and went to the fire, where they did at a ſafe diſtance behold the dreadfull ſtrokes he gave, how he layd on vvithout mercy, as men placed on Hills, through Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives, behold vvhole Armies fighting, and yet themſelves in no danger: The Gentlemen vvould not riſe from Table till <hi>Marriot</hi> had made an end of the ſpoyle, and could riſe tryumphant: <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi> having filled every Chink in his unſatiate gutts, gave the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing ſtroke and roſe up, and ſayd, Sir Knight thanke you for my Supper; Gramarcy Horſe quoth one of the Ladies, you might have ſayd for ten Suppers: He comes towards us, quoth another Lady, let us be gone, good novv lets be gone; let him be hanged quoth another Lady, never feare him, his anger is over novv, it is the uglieſt thing, quoth ſhee, that ever Dunghill produced: it grovving towards bed-time, ſome partly in feare of him, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to accompany them, left the Gentlemen vvith <hi>Marriot</hi> and retired to their Chambers, vvhere their tongues vvere ſo imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in deliniating <hi>Marriots</hi> parts, that one of the Ladies cryed out, For Heavens ſake talke no more on him, vvould <hi>I</hi> had touched the Monſter, for <hi>I</hi> dare ſay <hi>I</hi> ſhall dreame of him: The Gentlemen perceiving that <hi>Marriot</hi> vvas more a lover of the Kitchin then the Buttery, and vvas not company vvorth a Louſe, ſave for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall Art of eating; reſolved before they vvent to Bed to Souce all the meate he had Earrelled up in his Paunch, if all the Drink in the Buttery vvould doe it, and there vvas good ſtore: <hi>Marriot</hi> vvith much intreaty vvas dravvne to the Buttery, but not vvith
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166185:12"/>halfe the willingneſſe a Beare is to the Stake, healths paſt about, Gentlemen what mean you quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> my guts will hold no more, but they plyed him ſo nimbly with mixed Drinks, that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi> having but a weake head, was knockt down with drink, and ſo to his Chamber they went with him, and gave him the parting cup, which being unable to take, he tumbled into Bed like a Boare into his Sty, where no ſooner entred but you might heare by his ſnorting how ſafe and ſecure he was: And ſo the Gentlemen left him to the mercy of his Fate, and ſo went to conſult how they might make ſport the next day with him; and having laid their Plot handſomly, the next day they put it in practiſe, which is ſet down in the next enſuing Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>How they make</hi> Marriot <hi>beleive that he is poyſoned, and what happened.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Gent. being to give their Verdits what ſhould be done with <hi>Marriot,</hi> but none of their Projects were worth mentioning to this of the Knights, which only was put in practiſe, as thus; the Knight ſaid, I have a Butler that is a good Taylor, and I will ſet him to work preſently, ſo he cauſed one of his Servants to fetch <hi>Marriots</hi> Cloaths down, which being done, ſets his Butler to take in his Dublet of each ſide, ſo much as he ſhould not be able to button it, and likewiſe his Breeches; now being ſo neatly done that none could ſuſpect it, his Cloaths were laid by his Bed again, and all the Servants were charged not to ſay any thing of it,
<note place="margin">This Doctor was one of the Gentlemen that was in the Houſe.</note> but to perſwade him that he was much ſwelled, and that without doubt he was poyſoned, and to tell him that there was a Doctor in the Houſe that could cure him if there were but the leaſt hope of life in him; ſo every one that was confederate in this buſineſſe, was inſtructed how to carry themſelves, and for this night they go to Bed, ſome not ſleeping, to think how the Proiect would work, paſſed away the time with other diſcourſe, and ſo till Morning,
<note place="margin">He wondred to ſee his Cloaths ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</note> which time they long expected; all being in a readineſſe in the Morning to wait <hi>Marriots</hi> riſing from his neſt, which at laſte he did with the geſture of a Mad-man, thinking ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely he had been poyſoned, and being perſwaded by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166185:12"/>of the Houſe, that it was nothing but poyſon could make him ſo; Sir ſaid one of the Servants, here is a Doctor in the Houſe, and if you pleaſe I will call him, without doubt he will cure you:
<note place="margin">He mends the matter.</note> Oh ſaid <hi>Marriot</hi> if you look to ſee me a live man, make no ſtay but go fetch the Doctor, <hi>I hope he is not kin to</hi> Balams <hi>Aſſe, which will not ſpeake without he ſees an Angell:</hi> Sir ſaid he,
<note place="margin">Marriot had but little mony.</note> this Doctor is ſo much a Gent. that he will not expect the leaſt reward from you that may be, away away, fetch him quickly or I dye, the Servant goes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to the Doctors Chamber, who as much deſired to be ſent for,
<note place="margin">The Servant needs not tell the Doctor his Errant. Hee feels his Pulſes The Doctor preſcribes him a Broath to drink. He was a Mountebanck. You may read of the making of this Broath. in his Diſtillato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> as <hi>Marriot</hi> did his coming; who when he came to Mr. <hi>Marriots</hi> Chamber ſaluted him, and told him that by ſome Accedent he had received Poyſon into his Body, that was of that ſubtle Nature, that would not make him ſick to the inward Vitals, but only ſwell out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly for the preſent, but if not prevented would kill him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately: But I will cauſe a Broath to be made for you preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that is as famous as <hi>Mounſicure Puentes antedote</hi> for expelling Poyſons; <hi>Marriot</hi> gives him many thanks for his Care, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires him that the Broath might be made out of hand, the Broath being made, the Doctor gave him ſtrait charge not to take above three ſpoonfuls in an houres time, this was a griefe to <hi>Marriot</hi> to ſee his allowance ſo ſmall: <hi>For the whole quart was no more in his Belly then a Man in Pauls;</hi> This was his griefe that by ſpoonfuls he muſt be fed, and to eate no other thing: It being now Dinner time, the Knight to torment <hi>Marriot,</hi> deſired him to come and ſit in the Parler to paſſe away time, <hi>Marriot</hi> thought it would be ſome eaſe to him, went with the Knight, who cauſed his Broath to be ſet by him, that as occaſion did ſerve, to give a taſte to his mouth, but when Dinner was ſet on the Table, oh Reader had you but ſeen his Countenance and Geſture, you would have admired to ſee a ſick man lay violent hands on all ſorts of Meate,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A good Sign in a ſick man, when he has a coming Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack. You would have thought he had plaid</hi> Hocus Pocus <hi>with it.</hi>
                  </note> and had eaten it, had not his Doctor with many intreaties deſired him to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and promiſing him that he would give him Meate which would digeſt with him, made him forbeare now to ſatisfie his greedy Appetite; the Doctor gave him the wing of a Pullet, which the Doctor did deſire him to mince very ſmall, but in the twinkling of an eye was vaniſhed, and deſired the Doctor to let him have ſome more meat; the Doctor more willing to pleaſe the Company with his Actions, then to fill his ungodly Stomack, diſmembred a Fowle of his quarters to give <hi>Marriot</hi> the Carkas to pick, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Sir eate as little as you can for to day, and to morrow you may eate your belly full, for then the danger will be paſt: <hi>Marriots Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly having more eares then his head, gave little heed to what the Doctor ſaid, but fell to his Carkas, that he made both Meate and Bones Inviſible.</hi> Saying, Sir, you Dyet me as if I had the Pox, but if I once get
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166185:13"/>out of your hands,
<note place="margin">They are never good that mind their bellies ſo much.</note> Ile never come under a Doctor again, <hi>I</hi> think no Phyſick like Kitchin Phyſick, but Dinner being ended which was a griefe to <hi>Marriot,</hi> the Doctor cauſed him to go to his Chamber, for feare of taking cold, ſaying, He would not forget him at Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, if you do ſaid <hi>Marriot</hi> I ſhall remember you, I make no doubt of it ſaid the Doctor, now taking his leave of <hi>Marriot,</hi> he went down to the Knight, to plot more miſchiefe on poor <hi>Marriots</hi> Body, which you ſhall heare in the next Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>Supped, and how the Butler made him drunk, and after took away his Doublet, letting it out to its old ſhape, and how he eate a Bitch baked in a Pye the next day.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT being now Supper time, the pretended Doctor ſent <hi>Marriot</hi> up a Chicken roſted, and bid the Servant tell him that he might drink a glaſſe of Sack after it, <hi>Marriot</hi> did not ſtay for a Knife but puld it a peices, throwing it down his throat without chawing, that thoſe Servants that ſtood by him, thought he took it to be a ſin to bite his Meate: <hi>Marriot</hi> deſired the Servant to give him ſome Sack, he anſwered that he muſt go to the Butler for it,
<note place="margin">He need not to intice him to eate or drinke.</note> 
                  <hi>Marriot</hi> bid him go ſpeedily, the Butler brought a Bottle which did hold a p ottle of Sack up to <hi>Marriot,</hi> and ſaid, Sir, I heard the Doctor ſay, that old Wine was excellent good for you, and would do you much good, and I have brought you that's right, come ſaid <hi>Marriot</hi> let's taſte it, I think you to be the beſt Doctor when all's done, the Butler fills him a Tankord of Sack, which he ſoon turnd off, ſaying, Tis good Sack indeed, but give me the other Draught, and then my Stomack will be warme, after he had drank he ſaid to the Butler, Friend have you no cold meate in your Buttery, you would much comfort me,
<note place="margin">A good ſigne in a ſick man.</note> 
                  <hi>for I am hungry even to Death:</hi> The Butler anſwered, I have ſome Fragments of roſt beefe and powdred beefe and ſuch things, which was left at Supper, and if you will accept of that I will fetch it, I, I, ſaid <hi>Marriot</hi> any thing that is fleſh the Butler fetcht up a Basket as if he had been to diſtribute a Dole to poor Folk, when <hi>Marriot</hi> ſaw the Meate, like a man over
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166185:13"/>Joyed, laid to the meate and bred,
<note place="margin">Al's one to him for he had loſt his taſte.</note> Orange pills and parings of Aples being altogether in the Basket, having now as he thought laid a good Foundation in his Belly: give me ſome Drink, they gave him Sack, too good for ſuch an ungodly Gut, he not leaving this Basket with any thing in it, ſaid to the Butler, well thou haſt ſaved my life by this meanes, and though my Body be ſweld to Night, I hope to Morrow I ſhall be Iuſty, for the very conceit of being poyſoned made me feeble: Sir ſaid the Butler, will you be pleaſed to pledge this Health, its to my <hi>Maſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Butler drank Beer.</note> yes ſaid <hi>Marriot</hi> in a whole Tankard of Sack, I will begin it ſaid the Butler, drinking off his Tankard, and fild it with Sack, which <hi>Marriot</hi> ſoon drank off, ſaying, I am ſleepy and would go to Bed, it being ready, they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed him, and laying himſelfe in his Bed, ſaid, Put out the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, for I ſhall ſleep preſently; the Butler taking his Dublet and Hoſe with him, and now having let them out to their old form, he laid them in the place where they were before.</p>
               <p>He then went to Bed, looking for the Morning more earneſt then a Lawyer would do for a Fee, to have ſhare of the ſport which followes in the next Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>roſe in the Morning and eate his Breakfaſt, and how he was dined with a Paſty, wherein was an old ſpaid Bitch baked, and what happened.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArriot</hi> having ſlept as long as he could, knocked for ſome of the Servants, to bring up a Light to him, for to take To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, one of the Servants brought up a Candle, ſaying, Sir, it is very earely, and there is no body up but the Cook and my ſelfe, I hope you will not riſe yet, no no ſaid <hi>Marriot, I will not diſturb you if you are preparing for Dinner,</hi> Sir ſaid the Servant, I am heating of the Oven for two Veniſon Paſties, there is alſo great ſtore of Proviſion to be dreſt for Dinner, go thy wayes ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> leave only the Candle with me; he having a Pipe which held halfe an ounce, ſmoaked the Room as if wet Straw had been ſet on fire, but when the Tobacco was out, he reſolved to try if his Cloaths would come together, he quickly put it in practiſe; <hi>The
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166185:14"/>Cloaths ſitting him as if they had been made for him:</hi> I wonder the Devill who would have worne them beſides himſelfe, now he walks like a new <hi>Alderman,</hi> looking much on himſelfe: was often aſayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Staires, but fearing leaſt he ſhould awake ſome of the houſe, did contain himſelfe, by walking without his ſhooes, which had they been on,
<note place="margin">He might onely have waked the Horſes ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the Stable.</note> moſt ſure the noiſe would have been ſuch as if a Horſe-Mill were going; but what with hunger and joy he takes his Shooes in his hand and diſcends the Staires, coming to the Kitchin haſtily, frighted the Cook almoſt out of his wits; his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance was ſo terrible, that the Cook thought he would have eaten all the Meate raw; but <hi>Marriot</hi> ſaid, Friend, I love your Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation and would not diſturb you, Sir, ſaid the Cook, I never uſe to have lookers on when I am at worke: <hi>The man will make you a fire in the Parler,</hi> I know Cooks are angry men ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> I ſhall leave you to your ſelfe: The Cook was moſt afraid that <hi>Marriot</hi> ſhould have ſeen the Bitch which lay ready to be put into a Pye for him, with Tobacco and other Ingredients, to make the fleſh relliſh ſomewhat better then ordinary: Now the Pye being finiſht, was ſet with the reſt to bake, the whilſt <hi>Marriot</hi> was not idle, but gave a terrible onſet to a great <hi>Suffolk</hi> Cheeſe, making both Meate and Parings quickly Inviſible; this being but Breakfaſt meate, or rather a preparative to his Stomack, yet with much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, paſt out the time till Dinner was ready. <hi>Marriot</hi> thought the time long, but at length the Knight with his Friends came to ſee <hi>Marriot,</hi> who was ſmoaking the houſe with his ugly great Pipe, they ſaid Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> what are you mad to come out of your Chamber to catch cold? <hi>Sir ſaid Marriot, I was not mad to ſtay there to be ſtarved both with hunger and cold.</hi> They asked him if he thinks his Stomack would ſerve him to eate a little Veniſon, no meat comes amiſſe to me, for I have a good appetite; Dinner coming to the Board broke off the diſcourſe; <hi>but not Marriots Stomack:</hi> The Ladies alſo appeared, ſmiling at his looks, and deſire no other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>port, but to ſee him eate his Paſty which was provided for him; being all ſet at Table, <hi>Marriot</hi> fell to ſome powdred Beefe, Sir, ſaid the Knight, do not ſpoyle your ſtomack, there is more choiſer meate provided for you, I thank you Sir, this will ſerve the mean time; but the Paſties appeare, one for the upper end and one for <hi>Marriot,</hi> the Knight deſired <hi>Marriot</hi> to feed heartily, do not feare it Sir, for I have been long abſent from Victuals, but Ile pay it now; do, do, Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> and ſpare not, for twas provided for you; he preſently laid his truſty Blade on the walls of this Pye,
<note place="margin">The Bitch bee meant. Inſtead of Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets.</note> that he made it levell to the Plate: Yet after this he fell to ſix beare Cats, which were preſented before him in a Diſh, in whoſe bellies were diſſolved a pound of Candles, with the Herb called <hi>Spurgs,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:166185:14"/>which without doubt would looſen his Belly to ſome purpoſe. But the ſport was to come: Now Dinner being ended, many merry diſcourſes paſt between Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> and the young Ladies, but the Maids of the Houſe deſired their Lady, that they may have leave to ſhew one Chriſtmas Gamble, leave being granted them by the Knight and his Lady, the Knight deſired to know what it ſhould be, one of the Maids anſwered thus, Sir, you have been at great expences with Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> and tis time he repaire home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and if you give me free leave, Ile ſatisfie you, as ſhall appeare in the next Chapter following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>How the Servants of the Knights Houſe ſerved</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot <hi>a trick, and ſent him going to</hi> London.</head>
               <p>THE Servant Mayd began, Sirs you ſhall know this plot is thus; we have got Horſe haire cut very ſmall, with bay Salt beat together, which we will ſtrow in his Bed, that being once layd downe he ſhall never reſt in quiet, for his Cloaths ſhall be ſauced a little with the ſame ſpice, that he ſhall think he hath the pocky Itch: The Knight hearing this new project, laughed heartily, ſaying, Doe what you will, I ſhall winke at it: Now after a long Supper <hi>Marriot</hi> was ſent to Bed with a Fox at his tayle; now the ſport begins, for <hi>Marriot</hi> was no ſooner in the Bed, but he ſwore it was full of Fleas, ſtinging moſt violently that he was not able to lye there any longer, and at laſt roſe, but they had ſpiced his Cloaths alſo, which hee having put on, was in a worſe condition then before, ſwearing that he thought it would make him goe mad, they perſwade him to ſit ſtill, which he was as able to doe as to build a Church, he like a Fencer ſtood ſhruging and rigling his Body, that they that were preſent, could not forbeare laughing, <hi>Saying one to the other, now it works: Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi> would preſently go to the Knight, and acquaint him what tricks his Servants had put on him, the Servants perſwaded him to the contrary, but he is reſolute, and in a great fury goes out of the Chamber, ſtamping as if all the Horſes were dancing a Caranto, till he came to the Knights chamber Door, where with a hoarce voice he ſaid, Though it have been my goodneſſe to ſpend ſome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:166185:15"/>idle time with your Worſhip, and to make you laugh and your friends; I thought I had ſhewed you ſport enough in the day time, to have been a ſufficient protection for me at night, and not to be made dance like a halfpenny hot Loafe with q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſilver in it, I ſhall take my leave of your Worſhip though it be late, I may finde a Lodging ſome where: The Knight ſpeaks to Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> ſaying,
<note place="margin">With the Doggs he may.</note> Sir, be not angry with me, for if I knew who they were that thus have played the Knave with you, J ſhould turn them out of my houſe for your ſake: <hi>Marriot</hi> was even crying ripe for vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his misfortune. The Knight commanded his ſervants to pul of thoſe ſheets from the bed, and to lay on freſh, and to give him a Shirt to put on, whilſt his own was waſhed; <hi>Marriot</hi> gives the Knight many thanks, promiſing to ſhew him the uttermoſt of his skill at any time, ſo for that Night he went to Bed, and in the Morning he would take his Journy, the Knight gave Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> a Peice, to beare his Charges till he came to <hi>London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">No body would ſtay him.</note> ſo <hi>Marriot</hi> bid them Farewell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>How be departed from the Knights, for to take water for Billings-Gate, and how he eate Oysters there, and what befell him.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Horſe being ready for Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> and another for a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to conduct him to <hi>Graveſend:</hi> The Knight with the reſt of the Gentlemen went to ſee him take horſe, for this is the laſt trick they meant to ſhew him: They had ſadled a Golt that was to be backed, which they knew would throw him: The Ladies were got all to a Gallery, that looked to the Court, aſſuring themſelves of ſport: <hi>Marriot</hi> was now taking leave of them all, and by the help of Steps for the purpoſe, got up, but the Colt ran backward and rubbed his Leggs againſt the Walls, ſometimes riſing before and leaping, <hi>Marriot</hi> cryes out, I ſhall fall, hold the Horſe, but every one looked on, but none helped him; ſo at the laſt down he came tumbling, which made them laugh, nay do not laugh ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> for I might have broken my neck; really ſaid the Knight,
<note place="margin">He ſayd true enough.</note> be not angry with any of us, for we never ſaw any one fall from his back before; ſo he commanded another Horſe to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:166185:15"/>fetched for him, pray ſaid <hi>Marriot</hi> let me ſee ſome body on his back, for I am weary of falling, one of the Servants rid the Horſe about the Court, I ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> I wiſh I had rode him firſt, and then my bones would not have paind me now: Being mounted he took his leave of them, and rod as he was guided to <hi>Graveſend,</hi> where he took Boate for <hi>Billings-Gate,</hi> where being come, he ſaw many Boates which brought Oyſters Loaden very full: He ſaid to one of the Maſters of the Boate, Friend, what ſhall I give you to fill my belly full of Oyſters, and I will finde Bread, Beer, Oynions, Vineger, and Pepper; Sir ſaid the Boate-man, you ſhall give me but two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and you ſhall eate till your belly is full, my man alſo ſhall help you to open them, I yeild to this bargain ſaid <hi>Marriot:</hi> Now <hi>Marriot</hi> diſcends into the Boate where the Oyſters were, ſending the Boy for a ſix penny Loafe, two pennyworth of Oynions, Pepper and Vineger, three Flagons of Beer to waſh them down, this is to comfort me ſaid <hi>Marriot</hi> after all my ſorrowes,
<note place="margin">He ſpeaks to the Boat-man.</note> for J have had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of late; well be not angry at your Bargain, for <hi>I</hi> think <hi>I</hi> ſhall eate out my two ſhillings in Oyſters, my Stomack is ſtill good, Boy fetch me the other ſix penny Loafe, and three Flagons of Beer, and <hi>I</hi> ſhall have done preſently: The Devill do thee good with them, for <hi>I</hi> do verily beleive that you have eaten three Buſhels, thou ſhalt never eſcape thus, you may eate what you pleaſe, but Ile warrant you ſhall pay for them before you go out of this Boate: Friend ſaid <hi>Marriot I</hi> made a bargain with you, and <hi>I</hi> will make you ſtand to it; who the Devil will fill your belly with poore <hi>Iohn</hi> for forty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, much more with Oyſters for two ſhillings: Friend ſaid <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot I</hi> am a Lawyer and can be even with you at ſometime or other, what <hi>I</hi> warrant, you are the great Eater of <hi>Grayes-Inne,</hi> if you be,
<note place="margin">He geſſes well.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-board you go, for <hi>I</hi> will not have ſuch gormodizing in my Boate: By the Lord <hi>Harry</hi> tell me your Name, for Ile know,
<note place="margin">He is in earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</note> my Name is <hi>Marriot Jack,</hi> is not his name <hi>Marriot</hi> that we heard ſuch talk of, yes yes that is his name, well we will throw him into the <hi>Thames,</hi> and had not ſome Gentlemen come by,
<note place="margin">He ſpeaks toone by.</note> without doubt they had put it in practiſe, but the Gentlemen called Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> who flung down the two ſhillings, and made haſt to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, ſaying, <hi>I will eate no more Oyſters at your Boate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">He was out of the Boat firſt.</note> 
                  <hi>you keep ſuch a quarrelling for an Oyſter or two, well you Doggs,</hi> Ile be even with you if you come neer <hi>Grayes-Inne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:166185:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>dined at the three Kings, and what happened.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Marriot</hi> being now come with the Gentlemen to the three Kings, where were many Gentlemen to Dine, the Gentlemen preſented Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> as a Rarity among them, ſaying, It was our Fortune to ſave this Gentleman out of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Morning, and for our love he hath graced us with his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; we ſaw him merrily at Breakfaſt with Oyſters, they were like to have coſt me deare ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> for they threatned to throw me into the River, which without doubt had been, if you had not Countenanced me: I was in diſpaire till I ſaw your ſweet Faces, which were more comfort to me at that time, then a Repreive to a Theefe; for I was in almoſt as much danger: But I thank God and theſe good Gentlemen, I have eſcaped their Tyranous Proiect: Well to Dinner Gentlemen, Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> pray be no Stranger, but eate heartily, we all came to be merry: I know ſaid <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> your Mirth much lyes in me, but my Stomcak is almoſt ſpoyld, and I will not be laughed at, for my ill work-manſhip, well Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> do your beſt and it ſhall ſuffice, for we will preſſe nothing on you; <hi>Marriot</hi> fell upon the powdred Beefe, then to a leg of Pork: Hens and Capons were of ſuch light digeſtion, that he ſcarſe felt their going down; piſh, Tarts were but tryfles, but after his good Dinner came Cheeſe and Apples, <hi>I</hi> would ſaid <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> I had one hundred of good Pippins here, why ſaid one of the Gentlemen, would you eate them, I and thank you too, you ſhall have them then; they being brought, he never pared them, but made both Rines and Coares Inviſible: This being a ſufficient Digeſtion for his Dinner, deſired leave of the Gentlemen to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, they having had ſport enough with him, gave him leave to take his own time, thus he left the Gentlemen for that preſent, and went to his Lodging.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:166185:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>eate a Munkey baked in a Pye, in ſtead of a Hare.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Knight who lived neer the Kings Gate in <hi>Holborn,</hi> bought a Muncky of that Reverent Matron <hi>Mall Thrift,</hi> but being not fed as he uſed to be, dyed; for whoſe loſſe many of thoſe that loved his apiſh Tricks, mourned: but the Knight being frol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, laid a Wager with a young <hi>Eſq</hi> that he would produce a man that ſhould eate the <hi>Munckey,</hi> in ſtead of a Hare; the Wager was not great, but the paſtime to ſee any man ſo groſly miſtaken: The Knight preſently called his <hi>Cook,</hi> and bid him bake this <hi>Munckey</hi> in the form of a Hare Pye, which being done, Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> was ſent for; and becauſe the Boyes ſhould not run hallowing after him, the Coach was ſent; the Foot-man delivers his Meſſage thus; Sir, my Maſter would intreat your company at Dinner, he has no Strangers, only his owne Family; the chiefeſt thing he deſires of you, is to certifie him of ſome Points in Law, for part of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is Morgaged to a cunning Uſurer, whom he doubts will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, without your Counſell helps him; I'le warrant ſaid <hi>Marriot</hi> I ſhall do it if it be to be done:
<note place="margin">His Cloak was ſo greaſie he was loath to put it on.</note> J will but fetch my Gowne and go with you; Having put on his Gowne, he came to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant again, ſaying, What Houſe doth your Maſter keep? a Noble Houſe Sir, for you may come in a Morning and finde our Celler a foot thick in <hi>March</hi> Beer, here a <hi>black Jack and there a Flagon,</hi> ſtanding in it like Towers and Steeples in a drowned City: There is Houſe-keeping Sir; I marry ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> there is a Houſe wel kept indeed, nay Sir, by this meanes we may make my Maſter a better houſe-keeper, then ere his Father or Grand-Father were before him; for they were uſed to ride every day a Hawing and Hunting, my Maſter keeps the houſe ſometimes for two or three yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and what's the cauſe, nothing but our mirth? our <hi>Randans, our tara Tantaras</hi> — Oh the only way in the World to make a Gentleman a houſe-keeper.</p>
               <p>I ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> but what meate do you keep? We have alwayes great ſtore of all kinde of Proviſion in the houſe, let us away ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> I long till I am there, ſo he went into the Coach and was quickly at the Knights, where he was entertained with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:166185:17"/>being brought into the Parler, he ſaw the Cloath laid, and great Preparation, which made him rejoice much; the Knight with his Friend came and ſaluted this grave Counſellor, giving him many thanks, that he would vouchſafe to come at ſo ſhort a warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<note place="margin">Marriot <hi>eates alwayes of that Diſh which ſtands next him</hi>
                  </note> Sir, I deſire you to ſit down, and take part of our ſmall Commons, I thank you Sir I ſhall not ſpare, The Pye being brought and ſet before <hi>Marriot,</hi> which he ſoon devoured, the Knight asked him how he liked the Pye, very well ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> but the bones were mighty ſtrong; the Knight deſired to ſee one of the bones,
<note place="margin">Munkies bones are ſo.</note> call's his <hi>Cook,</hi> ſaying, What Pye was this, a Hare Pye Sir, did you ever ſee ſuch a bone in a Hare ſaid the Knight, I forty ſaid <hi>Marriot; John</hi> ſaid the Knight if you will not tell me what it was I ſhal turn you away: why then Sir, it was the <hi>Munckey</hi> which dyed: Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> ſaid the Knight, you are a fit Counſellour for the Devill, that doth not know a <hi>Munckey</hi> from a <hi>Hare;</hi> with this <hi>Marriot</hi> roſe from the Table, and ſaid, is this your Noble houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping to poyſon a poor Gentleman, whereat they fell a laughing, and <hi>Marriot</hi> went to his Lodging with many Boyes attending him, crying, <hi>Marriot, Who eate the Munkey.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>How M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
                  </hi> Marriot <hi>eate an Ordinary that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for twenty men.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THERE were certain Gentlemen which frequented an Ordinary, but having had ſome diſtaſte, reſolved to vex the People of the houſe by ſome meanes, and by chance met with Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> asked him if he would go with them to Dinner, with all my heart quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> but do not the People know me, if they do I ſhall not be admitted to the Table: let us alone to carry the matter, for you and I will go firſt in, and I will call you by another name, and not one will ſuſpect you; <hi>Marriot</hi> now walks boldly with the Gentleman, and being come into the Chamber, was ſeated in a great Chaire, the reſt of the Gentlemen preſently came, and being all acquainted with the buſineſſe ſate them down, as their uſe was, to play. But Dinner being come up, they left off and ſate them down, forbidding any Servants to be in the Room, only two of their owne, becauſe they had private Diſcourſe: The Meate being all on the Table, they deſired Mr.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:166185:17"/>
                  <hi>Marriot</hi> to fall on, and not to delay any time, he quickly took their adviſe, and vanquiſhed all that ſtood before him, to the amazement of the Beholders, the Gentlemen not having as yet unfolded their Napkins, nor taſted of a bit of the meate, ſate ſtill, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to keep him company: he having now finiſht his task, aroſe from the Table and walked a little; but the Gentlemen adviſed him to lay his halfe Crowne under his Trencher and to walk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<note n="†" place="margin">It was given him.</note> 
                  <hi>Marriot</hi> took their counſell, and away he went with one of the Gentlemens Servants, no more notice being taken of him then another: The Gentlemen, preſently knocked for the Maſter of the houſe, asking if they ſhould ſtay his leaſure for a Dinner, the Hoſt told them that he had ſent them a ſufficient Dinner, they deſired him to come in and ſee, if there be any thing that will but ſatisfie hunger, much leſſe variety, as is here expected; the Hoſt looking on the Table ſaw many Diſhes, but could not perceive what had been in them, they were ſo cleanly licked; one of the Gentlemen ſaid, <hi>You may ſee Sir, what a ſleight Ordinary you keep, that one man can eate that which you provide: for twenty:</hi> If you will provide us now a Dinner we will pay for it, for the Gentleman has left his halfe Crowne for what he has eaten: The Hoſt not willing to looſe all his Gueſts at once, provided them a Dinner preſently, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things extraordinary provided: they brought M. <hi>Marriot</hi> thither no more to Dinner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>How Mr.</hi> Marriot <hi>eate eight pound of Corrans, with one pound of Tobacco in them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT happened that Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> was walking alone by <hi>Grayes-Inne</hi> when ſome Gentlemen eſpyed him being in a Grocers ſhop,
<note place="margin">The Plot's a making.</note> who ſent the Boy to deſire him to come to them, <hi>Marriot</hi> preſently came, asking their pleaſure with him, one of the Gentlemen ſaid, I have laid a Wager on your head,
<note place="margin">Marriot <hi>deſires that none ſhould looſe their wagers of his perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances.</hi>
                  </note> and I hope you will not let me looſe it, not by any meanes ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> if I can help it: It is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus, I have laid ten ſhillings that you will eate eight pound of Corrans in one houre, Sir ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> before you ſhall looſe I will try my beſt; the Corrans being weighed, out were put all in, to a great Bowle, where doubtleſſe they had conveyed. Tobacco, yet in his eating them, they could not diſcern whether he taſted it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:166185:18"/>or no, he had no ſooner done, but he fell to vomitting, having eaten much that day, all would not lye in his Stomack, but flew out at both ends; the Gentlemen preſently hired a Cedan and ſent him to his Lodging where he was made clean, but the Cedan men curſed him, for the Chaire was not ſweet again in a Month.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>How M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
                  </hi> Marriot <hi>was pawn'd by ſome Gentlemen at a Taverne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere were certain Gentlemen at a Tavarn, who in a Morning made ſuch haſte, that they had ſpent all their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney before Dinner-time, and knew not at the preſent where to get a Dinner; but one of them being a notable Shifter ſaid, Let me alone to be Purver to day for you all, ſaying, I will firſt ſend for Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> to come hither, and when he is here, we will tell him that we have a noble Dinner providing, which will make him ſtay the dreſſing of it, and I dare to pay your Reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning if he doth not: <hi>Marriot</hi> was ſent for, who ſoon came, giving the Gentlemen many thanks for their love: One of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſaid,
<note place="margin">Marriot <hi>liſsens to him.</hi>
                  </note> Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> I hope you will accept of our ſmall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, provide your Stomack, for I will tell you your Cheer: There is firſt a legg of Porke and green ſauce, a legg of Mutton roaſted with Anchovy Sauce,
<note place="margin">But not his Stomack.</note> two Pullets and a Gooſeberry Tart: <hi>Marriots</hi> mouth watering, ſaid, Why do you not get good Beefe, wherein a man might looſe his Knife, that is meat which will ſtay in the Stomack, theſe light things will digeſt preſently: Meat being on the Table,
<note place="margin">The Pork was powdred to the purpoſe.</note> they ſate down, placing Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> at the upper end of the Board, that he might have the more elbow room: they all fed heartily, but <hi>Marriot</hi> had done with the leg of Pork, before they had eaten two ſlices of their Mutton, which they ſet preſently to him that he might looſe no time, ſo they fell to their Pullets, but they had ſearſe done carving when he was ready for his ſhare: Having now made an end of his Dinner, the Gentlemen drank to him in a glaſſe of Sack, ſaying, Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> I hope you have eaten that which pleaſeth you, the Pork was ſalt indeed, but a cup of Sack will waſh it down: <hi>Marriot</hi> took off his Glaſſes till he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ſleepy, and taking a nap in a Chaire, the Gentlemen
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:166185:18"/>ſaw it was time now or never to be gone, made down the Staires privately and went away, the Drawer coming in, asked Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi> where the Gentlemen were gone, I ſee them not ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">He was ſcarce awake.</note> then you muſt pay the Reckoning, I'le pay but my ſhare ſaid he, and ſo was going down Staires, but the boy prevented him by calling his Maſter, who cauſed Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> to pay the Reckoning, <hi>Marriot</hi> ſaid, <hi>I</hi> was never pawnd before, but this ſhall be a warning to me not to ſleep again in a Tavarn: and with a gaſtly Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance walked away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>How, Mr.</hi> Marriot <hi>was apprehended upon ſuſpition of stealing</hi> Gent. Doggs, <hi>and the merry ſport they had with him before a Juſtice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Marriot</hi> being but a mallencholly man; ſtill thought on ſome way or other to paſſe away idle time, and at laſt it came in his minde to go a fiſhing with an Angle, whereby there might ariſe profit as well as paſtime, ſo he went to <hi>Pauls</hi> and bought him a very ſtrong Rod, and asked for the ſtrongeſt Line he had, the Man ſhewed him a Pyke Line, the Hook having a double partition, he liking it, paid for them, and went away to <hi>Newgate</hi> Market, where he bought a Bullocks Liver to baite his Hook with; <hi>He thought all things would bite at Bullocks Livers,</hi> and hearing that it was good fiſhing <hi>Weſtward,</hi> went in a Boate to <hi>Braineford,</hi> where he reſolved to lodge all Night; his Liver and other Inſtruments he had in a Bagg which he carryed to the Kings Armes,
<note place="margin">He needed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but meat for his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack.</note> where being in ſome diſcourſe with his Land-Lord, he ſaid, that the reaſon he came into the Countrey, was to take a little pleaſure in Fiſhing, and to get him a Stomack: <hi>Marriot</hi> after he had eaten ſome ſmall matter, went to bed: the Hoſt being glad he had ſuch a Gueſt as he was, to draw company to his houſe, did acquaint ſome certain Gentlemen that lived thereabouts, they having notice hereof, reſolved to play a mad Prank with <hi>Marriot,</hi> ſo they acquainted a Juſtice of the Peace,
<note place="margin">Moſt are ſo.</note> who was as very an Aſſe as themſelves, but they deſired his Warrant to apprehend <hi>Marriot,</hi> upon ſuſpition of ſtealing Doggs to eate; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got this Warrant, they implyed a Conſtable to ſerve it, who
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:166185:19"/>was as much an <hi>Innocent</hi> as the reſt. In the Morning Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> went forth,
<note place="margin">They were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed before what to anſwer him.</note> to aske whether it were good time to go a Fiſhing or no, the Water-men told him, very good time Sir, to catch Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons or Jacks or ſuch great fiſh: I will go with you preſently, I will but fetch my <hi>Tackling,</hi> having diſcharged the houſe, away he goes to the water ſide, where Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> went into a Boate, and ſaid to the Water-man, carry me now where the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Fiſh lyes, I ſhall Sir, ſaid the Water-man do my beſt endeavour, where having-ſet him on ſhoare; <hi>Marriot</hi>-puls out his <hi>Tackling,</hi> and baites his <hi>Hook</hi> with a peice of Liver enough to choake a Dogg: It being a deep place many Eeles reſorted to his baite, many times he puld them to the top of the water, but caught none; he thought his own way beſt, and ſo walked further, but being watched by thoſe Gentlemen, who as he was going over a Feild, to a better place to ſtand to fi h in: a Conſtable appeared and told him he had a Warrant for him, and he muſt go preſently before a Juſtice of the Peace, <hi>Marriot</hi> wondred what ſhould be the matter, but knowing that it could not be helpt, went with the Conſtable; the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being come before the Juſtice, who demanded of them what they had to ſay to Mr. <hi>Marriot;</hi> one of the Gentlemen ſaid, Sir, upon ſuſpition of ſtealing our Doggs, for he carryes Inſtruments for the purpoſe, he hath a line of Whipeord of thirty yards long, with a Hook that is wired two foot: With theſe and the like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments he doth many miſchiefs; alſo catching <hi>Ducks</hi> and other poor Creatures, as ſilly Piggs; for the Doggs they ſupply his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack in the Vacation, and in the Term time he either is, or makes his Clyents to be at the charge of the roaſting of the Pigs and Ducks, and the like: How is that quoth the Juſtice, why ſuch Deſignes may undoe a whole Country: Sir, Sir, (quoth he) theſe Inſtruments are unſufferable, how do you know how many poor People may be undone by your Engines. I am a Gentleman and a Lawyer quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> and know what belongs to things of this Nature as well as your ſelfe, not unlikely quoth the Juſtice, but Sir, Sir, you muſt know where you are, and who you are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that I do very well quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> you are a Juſtice they ſay: Put caſe
<note n="*" place="margin">Marriot <hi>puts him a Caſe.</hi>
                  </note> I did uſe ſuch <hi>Tricks,</hi> you have not taken me in the Manner, nor ought any man to ſuffer for his Belly, for that is moſt an end the Suſterer: Where where quoth he is the <hi>Pigg or the Duck</hi> I did take, ſhew me any and what; and Faith let them be roaſted, and we'l laugh a little: With that the Gentlemen there laughed heartily: Hold hold quoth the Juſtice, this is no laughing Matter (and yet could hardly forbeare it himſelfe) of what Innes of Court are you, <hi>Grayes-Inne</hi> quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I honour the Place very much quoth the Juſtice, but <hi>Mr. Marriot</hi> it is a great
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:166185:19"/>diſhonour to the houſe, for a Member hereof to become a Dogg-ſtealer, I profeſſe quoth <hi>Marriot</hi> they wrong me, I came for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but my pleaſure, well replyed the Juſtice, for no other reaſon then that you are of that honourable houſe, I ſhall remit the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and quit you, but have a care Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> how you come a fiſhing in theſe parts agen, I warrant you Sir quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I have a good warning, and ſo took his Journy home-ward, where being Arrived, he told his Land-Lord how he had been ſerved, and vowed never to go a fishing more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP XX. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>was privately Invited to a Supper in the City, which was appointed for the making of two Neighbours friends, which had formerly been at variance, and how he was diſcovered: And how both he and the reſt of his Company were diſmiſt without their expected Supper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT happened that two Citizens of <hi>London</hi> had a falling out, whether it were for their own honeſty or their Wives, I know not, which I ſhall not here queſtion; but by ſome Neighbours they were adviſed to put it to Arbitration, each man was to chooſe two ſufficient men in the Pariſh, to end this Controverſie, rather then to go to Law to ſpend much Money on both ſides, and neither the Gainer; all partyes are agreed to put it to Arbitration, which accordingly was done; and he who was ſuppoſed to have done the wrong, was by theſe learned men, judged to give the party wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a Supper for himſelfe and his Friend; the time and place was appointed, and all are Friends again.</p>
               <p>Yet he who had received the wrong, and not well pleaſed with the Reſult of the Arbitration, ſtill retained an inward Grudge, though he ſeemingly carryed a faire out-ſide to the other, and did ſtudy how to vex him: at laſt he thought, that if he could get Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> with him, hee ſhould be ſufficiently revenged on him: for he knew that his Stomack was able to undo two ſuch houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers as he was, might he have but a full Table continually, he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:166185:20"/>preſently ſent for Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> and gave him the whole circumſtances of the buſineſſe, and declared the cauſe of his ſending for him, which was this.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> there hath lately been ſome fallings out, betwixt one of my Neighbours and my ſelfe, wherein I have received much Damage and Wrong, the Particulars thereof will be too long to recount unto you, and keep you from hearing that, which you ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be the occaſion of my ſending for you at this time, you ſhall go as my Friend, and at the Supper I wiſh you to feed heartily, for it will be a great ſatisfaction to me, to ſee him vex at the ſpoyle of his meate; do you think that your Stomack is able now to give a finiſhing ſtroake to the meate that ſhall be brought to the Table: when <hi>Marriot</hi> heard this, his ſolid Countenance changed into a ſmile, thinking himſelfe halfe at ſupper already, ſaying, Sir, I am ſo well prepared for ſuch an Encounter, that had I faſted a Week, I could not have a better Stomack then now I have: for were there more meate then I gueſſe there is, I durſt attempt it all my ſelfe: Bravely ſpoken Mr. <hi>Marriot,</hi> you ſhall be my only Champion in this buſineſſe, and <hi>I</hi> dout not but that we ſhall remain Conquerours in our Enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marriot</hi> who for ſuch a buſineſſe needed not to be much intreated: but ſtreight way Harneſſed himſelfe, and a long with the Meſſenger he goes; being now come to the Citizens houſe, he was better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed of the matter, and away they go to the place where they ſhould have their Supper, being come, they were led into a faire Room where the Cloath was laid, Bread and Salt on the Table, and other neceſſaryes on a ſide Cubboard: <hi>Marriot</hi> heard the <hi>Jack</hi> go, but as yet had not ſmelt the meate; his Stomack being raw, fell upon a French Roule to appeaſe the wateriſh Humours that did trouble him: But the meate ſtaying ſomething long, cauſed <hi>Marriot</hi> to eate all the reſt of the Bread that was on the Table; the Maſter of the houſe came up to welcome the Gentlemen, but when he ſaw the Salt ſtand on the Table and no Bread by it, knocked for his Servant to come up, being come, he ſaid, Is there no Bread to ſet on the Table, Sir, ſaid the Servant; I brought ſix french Roules up and ſet them on the board, Sir, ſaid <hi>Marriot,</hi> you need inquire no further for them, for being hot with walking, I love to eate a Cruſt, then ſaid the Maſter it is well enough, calling the Maid, whiſpered in her Eare, that ſhe ſhould carry the meate to a Neighbours houſe, and that he would be there preſently, for quoth he, here is the great Eater of <hi>Grayes-Inne,</hi> who will make no more of this Supper, then a Plow-man would do of a poached Egg: When the Servant was gone, the Maſter of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:166185:20"/>houſe ſaid to him who was his Adverſary, Sir, I alwayes had a ſuſpition of you, by reaſon of your equivocating, is this
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pointing to Mr.</hi> Marriot.</note> a fit man to be brought to an honeſt mans Table; away, away, you get no Supper here, for I will entertain no ſuch belly-Gods at my Table: Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> marched up towards him, ſaying, Sir, I deſire to be acommodated as well as any other Gentleman, but your ill bred Citizens have no more manners then a Horſe, and do not know when they are in the preſence of a Gentleman how to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: I would have you to know Sir, that many Lords and Knights are glad of my Company, and are you ſo nice; Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> ſaid the Citizen, They have money enough, and ſend for you only to make them ſport, my Purſe will not reach the paſtime, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whilſt tis time, go ſeek your Supper, for you get none here; when <hi>Marriot</hi> heard this Sentance paſt on his Belly, like a Beare bereaved of her Whelps, ſtormed, and went down the Staires, as if a Water-Mill had been going; you may conceive the Door was not ſhut againſt him, but rather ſet wide open, to let out him and his <hi>ſtomack,</hi> which otherwiſe might have been the diſtruction of more Meat then many a Butcher kills in a <hi>Week,</hi> had it been there dreſt, his <hi>Stomack</hi> was then at ſuch a height: but <hi>Marriots</hi> Friend came down, and with the beſt words he could uſe deſired his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and for to ſtop both his Mouth and his Belly, had him to an Ale-houſe, and gave him nine two penny loaves and two pound of <hi>Suffolk Cheeſe,</hi> which for the preſent did allay the knawing of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Worm which he hath in his Maw, his Friend promiſing him a better Collation when they met next, parted, and <hi>Marriot</hi> went heavily to his Lodging.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>How</hi> Marriot <hi>accidentally lighted on a Legg of Porke, which was deſigned for the Dunghill, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving layne in Salt above halfe a yeare, and what happened after.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArriot</hi> walking ſolitarily alone, was by the hand of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence led to a place where he eſpyed a Damſell throwing a legg of Porke to a Dunghill; oh quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you are not aſhamed to throw away good meat, you know not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:166185:21"/>the price of it: Sir ſaid the Maid, this meat hath layne in a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Tub unknown this halfe yeare or more: no matter no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> give it me and I will make a rare Diſh of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Bleſſe me God what good meat is this, much pitty it were to throw ſuch to Doggs: I thank you faire Damſell for your love, I will get it ready for my Supper: So away he goes with his rich priſe, which had it been carryed to the <hi>Eaſt Indies</hi> and brought back again, it could not have been more ſalt then it was. Being come home he deſired ſome water to ſet it on, which was done accordingly; it being now boyled, <hi>Marriot</hi> fell to, and quickly picked the bones, but he complained that it was very ſalt, but to put away the thought of drink out of his minde, went to bed, thinking that ſleep would a peaſe his Drought, but it proved otherwiſe, for about Midnight he waked, thinking himſelfe to be neer ſome great fire, by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great heat he was in, ſtarted up and ran to his Window, crying out, fire, fire, murther, murther, at laſt his Land-Lord came up, asking him what was the matter, pray fetch me a Paile of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> for the fire is only in my belly: ſo you have not fired my houſe, I do not care if it were in your — his Land-Lady brought him up a paile of water, which he poured into his boyling Caldron, to appeaſe thoſe humours which would have run into a further diſtemper if not quenched in time: but <hi>Marriot</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to wiſh that the Doggs had eaten the Porke before he had ſeen it; but he ſaid, if they had, a thouſand to one but it had killed them, poor Creatures, and therefore I am glad I eate it my ſelfe: So de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring his Land-Lord not to take it ill that he knocked them up, at ſo unſeaſonable an houre, but his Land-Lord very civilly ſaid, Mr. <hi>Marriot, we are all ready at your knock,</hi> if it pleaſe you to have any more water before we go to bed, it ſhall be fetched, no more ſaid <hi>Marriot</hi> at this time; ſo laying him down, ſlept more quietly then before, his Land-Lord alſo went to bed, and did think becauſe Porke had ſo fired his Maw, that he would never love ſwines fleſh again: but he proved no <hi>Jew,</hi> for he was at Bacon the next day.</p>
               <p>There are more ſtories of his doubtleſſe (Reader) you have heard, but I have ſelected theſe as the only truths, and that you may know more of him, he lyes at a Joyners houſe in <hi>Grayes-Inne Lane,</hi> and there may finde him and his <hi>Stomack,</hi> up together any Morning.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:166185:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader, I ſhall trouble thee a little further, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy patience till I have revealed the chiefeſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits that he continually uſeth, as well in times of ſickneſſe as of health; they have been kept private theſe many yeares, and now come to light, publiſhed by a ſpeciall Friend to this Common Wealth, and for the benefit of all thoſe that are troubled with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Stomack, which craveth more then their Estates are able to ſatisfie, as M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>
               </hi> Marriot <hi>doth, to his great impoveriſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP I. <hi>How to make his Cordiall Broath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke three Sheeps Hinges with the Wooll on their Heads: Three dozen of Sheeps Trotters: Two Bullocks Livers, with halfe a peck of Otemeale; boyle all theſe in a Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron two houres, then ſtrain the Broath through a haire ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath, and let it coole: The uſe of it is to appeaſe grumbling in the Guts, or a wambling <hi>Stomack,</hi> by drinking one Gallon at a time, and eating the meate after it: this will preſerve you from hunger and wind in the <hi>Stomack,</hi> uſing it but once in two houres: <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By Mr. <hi>Marriot.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>His Pils to appeaſe hunger, ordinarily carried about him.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of Rye meale nine pound, Of Chandlers Graves three pound, of the skimmings of Hony one pound, warme water as much as will make it into a Paſte, then roule them up into a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:166185:22"/>dozen Balls, then put them into ſome boyling Broath, till they be through boyled, then ſet them to coole; but beware that the Doggs do not deceive you of them, as they have done him often times.</p>
               <p>THE chiefe uſe of theſe Pills are for travelling, for Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot</hi> carryed alwayes a dozen to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in the Term time for feare of fainting; his ordinary place for eating them, was in the dark place, neer the Common Pleas Treaſury, where one might ſee him ſwallow theſe Pills, as eaſily as an ordinary man would do a guilt Pill in the Pap of an Apple.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>A Purgation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Marriot</hi> would often follow the Farriars Rule for Dren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which Receit beſt agreed with his Body: for he would take Milk and Oyle with Aquavitae, Pepper and Brimſtone all mingled together, a Pottle at one time is nothing with him, to ſcoure his Maw.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Why he ſwallowes Bullets and Stones.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE heat of his <hi>Stomack</hi> is ſuch, that without ſuch a remedy he could not ſubſiſt; for when he hath gormandized himſelfe at ſome great Feaſt, ſtrait way he ſwallowes Bullets of almoſt foure ounces weight, which cauſes a preſent digeſtion: Alſo round Pebble ſtones he often ſwallowes, which cools his Maw.</p>
               <p>Theſe kinde of Tricks he hath, by which he puts down many of our new <hi>Juglers</hi> now a dayes, who will be an houre eating of a Cheeſe-Cake, he vanquiſheth all that dare oppoſe him in his Art.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:166185:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>How he orders his baked Meate, or his rare Diſh on Sundayes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Marriot</hi> out of niceneſſe, becauſe he would not have womens fingers in his meat, dreſſes his meat himſelfe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an earthen Pot which holdes halfe a buſhell, he fills it in this manner as followeth.</p>
               <p>Take a Bullocks head, the bones being chopped ſmall, and good ſtore of Onions and other courſe Hearbs which are eaſily to be got,
<note place="margin">Pepper nought for the Pox.</note> with an ounce of Pepper, for he ſcares no pox, as many Turnups as will fill the Pot, when he had layd all theſe in his Pot, he put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Gallon of Pumpe water, becauſe it ſhould not want moiſture, then with his owne pawes he carryes it to the Bake-houſe, ſtaying ſtill by it, fearing leaſt he ſhould be deprived of ſome of it in his abſence.</p>
               <p>He never goes to Church on a Sunday, but gives much atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Baker when he ſayes it is time to draw, which time being come, he carries his Pot home, and to Dinner he goes without lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Cloath,
<note place="margin">He buyes no new Bread.</note> firſt he cuts ſlyces of ſtale Bread and ſops them in this Reſtorative: He is a right Engliſh man, for he eates his Broath firſt, which being done, he ſends the meat to be boyled once more in his hot Maw, which hath ſo quick a digeſtion, that three Cookes are not able to provide him meat at all the motions of his Stomack: This being an abſolute remedy for the preſent, I have here ſet it downe for thoſe Stomacks that dare keep him company.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>How to make his rare Fiſh-broath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LIke a good Doctor he makes his broath; only in <hi>May</hi> or <hi>June,</hi> when <hi>Mackrell</hi> are ſixteen or twenty a Groat, and then he hath great skill in chooſing them, for none but the broken bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:166185:23"/>ones will ſerve his turne: but becauſe he would not be chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them, he will go to <hi>Billingſgate</hi> himſelfe, and will ſit on the ſtaires halfe a day, rather then be diſappointed: but ſeeing fiſh for his turne, preſently buyes three Groats worth, and puts them in his bag for the purpoſe, and away he comes home, getting water, and ſetting them on in his large Coldron, many hearbs he uſes, as Fennell, Bayes, Roſemary, and a few Leekes, but when it is boiling he skims it, becauſe it is to make broath, having ſo done, he lets them boyle a little, and then takes up his Fiſh and his hearbs, then he puts halfe a peck of Malt in, and boiles it again, his fiſh he ſets to coole, yet like a good Cooke, hee lickes his fingers as he is a dreſſing them, having now boyld his broath ſufficiently, he falls on it, and the fiſh, making no more of it, then the Welſhman did of his three peny Ordinary, who was ready for another, before he had done that he was about.</p>
               <p>The uſe he made of this broath and fiſh, was only as I conceive to get him a ſtomack, for he would often ſay, That fiſh was of a light digeſtion: therefore good for thoſe that have but a ſlight ſtomack at preſent, but deſire a greater,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>To make his cooling Sallet, to coole the Blood.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Am of opinion that he hath read <hi>Gerards</hi> Herball, or the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Plants, wherein partly he found this Receit, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inlarged by himſelfe, I thought fit to ſet it downe amongſt the reſt; he being a man of a hot Stomack, did uſe this Sallet following very often, wherein he found great benefit,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The way to make it is thus,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take as many Water-Creſſes as a large Flasket will hold, as many Radiſh tops, and halfe ſo many Colworts, boyle all theſe together for the ſpace of two houres,
<note place="margin">You may bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron.</note> then take them up without much ſqueizing, and put them in a halfe Tubb, putting thereto a Gallon of ſoure Ale, and a quantity of Gooſe-greaſe, ſufficient to give it a taſte, with a pound of Pepper ſtrewed upon it: This Sallet is excellent good to purge the blood, and to looſen the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this quantity being taken three ſeverall mornings in the weeke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:166185:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII <hi>How to make Mr.</hi> Marriots <hi>new Diſh, called a</hi> Frigazee.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MARRIOT</hi> hearing of a new Diſh that was much uſed at <hi>Oxford Cates,</hi> and in other places about the City amongſt Gallants, thought in his fanſie to make one that ſhould reſemble it, becauſe the materialls that were uſed in it, were too deer for him, but being a man of a rare Stomack, quickly gueſſed at ſomething that was eatable, though dreſſed in a ſtrange way; when he had thought upon all the materials of this Diſh, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to put it in practice, having gotten all the Ingredients toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to try this rare concluſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And thus he made it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He took three great Pomcitrons and pulled out the Curnels that were within them, then he pared the outſide rinde off, and then ſlyced them into thinn ſlyces, then he had many Apples which he ſlyced alſo, then he took two Bullocks Livers and ſlyced them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thinn and broad, then he layd a row of the former ſlyces in the bottome of his Oxe-cheek-pot, he peppered his Liver well, and layd a laying of one and a laying of another, till he had filled his Pott, ſtrowing many fine hearbs on the top of it, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> carryed it to the Bake-houſe, where he ſtayd till it was baked; being come home, he invited his Landlord to taſte of his new Diſh, who I dare ſware never ſaw the like before, but his Landlord knowing his Stomack, and that a — was as good for a Sow as a Pancake, prayſed his Diſh highly, ſaying, It is very good, but I have newly ſupped, therefore I deſire you to excuſe me to night, I ſhall leave none for to morrow, quoth <hi>Marriot,</hi> therefore ſtand to it now that you may ſay you have eaten of a rare Diſh, he not being over nice eate a bit or two with him, but I will not tell how ſick it made the poore old man, but it agreed with Mr. <hi>Marriot</hi> as if it had beene a Chicken roaſted, and ſerved in to his Table with Butter and Parſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, ſo excellent is his Stomack for digeſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
